here.
here.
learn how to play yatown
learn how to play yatown
bien hungry
bien hungry
Through rich
Through rich
ring
ring
applause
applause
Thank you.
Thank you.
Vice President Peng Xuming was supposed to host today
本来今天应该由彭旭明副院长来主持
But because he just took office
可是因为他刚上任
Then he has traveled with people before
那么他在之前已经跟人游
It was already ordered
原来就已经有预定的这个
so he can't come tonight
所以他今天晚上不能来
I want to help him host
要我来帮他主持
then today's
那么今天的
This topic is of great interest
這個題目是一個很引起大家關注的
Issues that have attracted great attention in the past ten or twenty years
近一二十年來非常引起大家關注的問題
it's climate change
就是氣候變遷的問題
I want to talk about climate change twenty years ago
我想二十年前談氣候變遷
When environmental changes talk about these things
環境變遷談這些東西的時候
At that time, these seemed relatively foreign to at least some people.
那時候這些至少都有個人而言好像比較陌生
But now it has become very urgent
可是現在已經變得非常的迫切
The first three weeks of our Academia Sinica
我們這個中研院前三個禮拜
In this place in Thailand, the Pacific Institute of Science and Technology is organized
在泰國的這個辦這個太平洋理理協會
PNC
PNC
In Bangkok, it happened to encounter this flood problem
在曼谷正好就是碰到這個洪水的問題
So this makes people feel that this issue is very urgent
所以這個讓人家覺得這個問題非常之急迫
So we are at Academia Sinica these days
所以我們這幾天在中研院
In addition to the feast of knowledge tonight
除了今天晚上的知識饗宴之外
We have an environmental history at the Renwen Pavilion
我們在人溫館有環境史
Conference on World Environmental History
世界環境史的會議
It's also worth going
也很值得各位去
Today we invited the speaker is this
今天我們請到了主講者是這個
Inter-director of the Special Review Researcher of the Environmental Change Center of the Academia Sinica
中研院環變中心的特評研究員間主任
Professor Liu Shaocheng
劉少成教授
Professor Liu is a member of the School of Physics at Cheng Kung University
劉教授是成功大學物理學院
Go to PizBall University in the United States to get a Ph.D. in physics
到美國PizBall大學得到物理博士
Since then he has stayed in the United States to work
此後他就留在美國工作
U.S. Oceanographic Service
曾經擔任過美國海洋大紀總署
Research Director of Daji Physics Laboratory
大紀物理實驗室的研究員主任
also served at the Georgia Institute of Technology
也到喬治亞理工學院擔任
Chair Professor of the School of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences
地球及大氣科學學院的講座教授
department head
系主任
He returned to the China Security Research Institute 12 years ago
12年前他回到中安研究院
That horse was first on Earth
那馬先是在地球所
Then came the creation of the Environmental Center
接著是開創環境中心
if memory serves me right
如果記憶沒錯的話
Gore won the Nobel Peace Prize
高爾獲得了諾貝爾和平獎
There seem to be more than 1000
好像有1000多張
Contributors also get a certificate
有貢獻的人也得到一張獎狀
Director Liu also got a
劉主任也得到一張
It can be seen that he has participated in the concern for a long time
可見他長期參與 關注
There are also research contributions in this area
還有在這方面的研究貢獻
We have gained great international
我們已經在國際上得到很大的
recall and affirm
回想和肯定
I am very happy to have the opportunity to invite him to give a speech today
今天非常高興能有機會邀請他來演講
And he's talking about the topics he's good at
而且講的就是他在行的題目
climate change in taiwan
台灣氣候變遷
The subtitle is Shock Mitigation and Adaptation
副標題是衝擊減緩跟調適
We now applaud Professor Liu
我們現在鼓掌歡迎劉教授
applause applause
掌聲鼓掌聲
Vice President Wang
王副院長
Everyone advanced
各位先進
Colleagues
各位同仁
Ladies
各位女士
hello gentlemen
各位先生大家好
global warming climate change
全球暖化氣候變遷這個問題
I believe everyone has heard it many times
我相信大家都是聽了不少次了
I was actually a feast of knowledge in 2004
我其實2004年的時候的知識的饗宴
Also talked about a topic quite related to this topic
也講到跟這個題目相當有關的一個題目
Actually today when I was preparing
今天其實我在準備的時候
Today I
我今天
I said that I must be completely different from that film in 2004.
我说我一定要跟2004那个东西啊那个片子要绝大部分不同
ah
啊
No
不
Of course, there will always be a few articles, and I counted them.
当然总总是会有几个几篇我还算了一下差不多啊
15% of the films are pretty close to last time
15%的片子跟上上次还是蛮接近的啊
No
不
This time this year
今年这一次啊
I'll show you guys look at our first one this one this one is very different
我给大家看看你看我们第一个这个这个是很不一样的
In fact, what do I say about that, that, and this movie?
其实我当那个那个这个片子说啥呢
Tell me, introduce me, introduce us to you
说啊介绍啊跟大家介绍我们
this is gone
这已经没有了
Whoops
哎呦
ah
啊
I'm afraid I can make a brighter one, and this one is basically invisible.
那个恐怕弄一个比较亮一点的这个基本上看不见了
I want to go to the back. This is basically the introduction.
我想去后面啊这个基本上这个介绍啊啊
This is, of course, the history that Vice President Wang is most familiar with.
这当然是我们王副院长最最熟悉的历史
OK Human Evolution History
OK 人类的进化的历史
The first green one is Lucy
第一个绿色的是Lucy
You see Lucy is very interesting
你看Lucy很有意思
I believe everyone has heard
我相信大家都有听过
Africa's first dug
非洲的第一个挖出来的
Lucy who looks like a human
看起来像人的Lucy
We suppose are all its descendants
我们suppose都是它的后代
Everyone also noticed that the original people in Beijing were
大家也注意到北京原人是在
This is about 3 million years
这个是差不多300万年
Peking Man was less than 1 million years old
北京原人是不到100万年
800,000 years
80万年
Then Homo sapiens was almost 200,000 years ago
然后智人又更差不多是20万年
And then until Homo sapiens came out
然后一直到智人出了
not exodus
不是出埃及籍
After leaving Africa
是出非洲以后
Then the first most important historical
然后第一个最重要的历史的
what happened was
发生的事情就是
Ancient civilization
古文明
Everyone probably knows about ancient civilizations that there are four ancient civilizations
古文明大家恐怕都知道有四个古文明
Since Father Wang is here, I won’t ask you what the four are.
因为王父在这我就不问大家四个是什么了
Originally, I thought it was because Father Wang knew too well
本来我想因为王父太清楚了
So I won't bring up this question any more
所以这个问题我就不再提出来了
Ancient civilization
古文明
Of course including China iQi
当然包括中国 爱奇这些
basically in almost
基本上都是差不多在
That is to say, from four thousand years to almost eight thousand years
就是说四千年到差不多八千年的时候
developed
发展出来的
From a climate point of view
从气候的角度来看
human evolution
刚才人的进化
Now here I am a
现在这里我这个是一个
This is time and this is temperature
这个是时间 这里是温度
zero degrees here
零度在这里
OK
OK
Of course, this so-called zero degree is only used to represent
当然这个所谓零度只是用来表示
is the current temperature before the industrial revolution
是目前的在工业革命之前的那个温度
because zero is here
因为零在这里
this is two degrees this is minus two degrees
这是两度这是负二度
OK
OK
Of course the dinosaurs were hot
那当然恐龙的时候很热
this is it
这个是啊
But what we just saw
不过我们刚才看到的
Ha, this ancient civilization is almost
哈这个古文明是差不多是
ah
啊
About five, six, five, or six thousand years ago
多少差不多五六五六千年的时候
ha
哈
it's here
在这里
OK
OK
this paragraph
这一段
this paragraph now
这一段现在
Of course, it is called the best period of the new climate.
当然被称为是全新式这个气候最佳期
OK
OK
ah
啊
Then why is this the best period for a new climate?
那这个为什么是全新式气候最佳期
it has its reasons
它是有它的原因的
at that time
在那个时候啊
it's time again
这里又也是时间
OK
OK
it's four thousand years
这是四千年
ten thousand years you see
一万年你看
four thousand to ten thousand years
四千年到一万年
you look at the northern hemisphere
你的你看这个北半球
all red and yellow
都是红的黄的
all on average
都是平均起来
Middle and high latitudes of the northern hemisphere
北半球中高纬度啊
almost two degrees
是差不多两度以上
this ratio
这个比
more than two degrees higher than now
比现在高两度以上
But in the low-dimensional sea
不过在低维度的海面
Ocean temperatures are relatively low
海洋温度是比较低的
So what I just showed you is here
所以刚才我给大家看的就是在这里
This is the best time for the new climate
这个是全新式气候最佳期
The best period is of course when the northern hemisphere was very warm just now
最佳期当然就是刚才北半球非常暖和的时候
Civilization develops when it's very warm
非常暖和的时候有了文明的发展
make it easy for everyone to think of
使大家很容易联想到
That is to say, the high temperature I showed you just now
就是说刚才我给大家看的高温度
That is to say, two degrees higher
就是说高了两度
compared with just now
跟刚才比较起来
You see, we humans have been talking about 3 million years since just now
你看我们人从刚才讲300万年
Lucy has basically been here since she started
Lucy开始以后基本上都在这里
you see it's very cold
你看都是非常冷的
cold to sometimes more than two degrees
冷到有时候超过两度
most of the time 80% of the time
大部分的时候80%的时间
We are in a much colder super than the current
我们是在差不多比目前冷超
almost once
差不多一度的情况下
develop there
在那里发展
evolve there
在那里进化
So from this point of view
所以从这个观点来说
We should be very suitable
我们人应当是很适宜
cooler earth
比较凉爽的地球
Than what two once looked like now
比现在两个一度的样子
But once we get here, than now
可是我们一到了比现在
hotter than we're used to
比我们习惯的时候热起来
culture
忽然就把文化
civilization
civilization
culture develops
对文化就发展出来
This is a very interesting phenomenon
这是一个蛮有趣的现象
I've actually always been interested in this
我其实一直对这个都很有兴趣
Here I also show you
这里我也给大家看一下
we are now greenhouse gas
我们现在温室气体
Scenarios for temperature increase by 2100
到2100年温度增加的情况
It's about 2 to 4 degrees
是差不多2到4度
i draw it here
我把它画在这里
2 to 4 degrees
2到4度
Everyone think about our
大家想想刚才我们的
It's almost over 2 degrees here
这里就是差不多超过2度
In fact, many people say
其实很多人就说
since we are here
既然我们在这里
culture develops so fast
文化发展那么快
so good
那么好
obviously the climate you see
显然气候你看
this too
这个也是
recognized worldwide
世界公认的
This is not a word I invented
这个不是我发明的字句
Here is another solid
这里还有一个实心式
best climate
气候最佳期
warmer
更暖和
OK
OK
and at that time it was true
并且那时候的确
The Earth's
地球的
productivity
productivity
yes
是
it is this
是这个
just say that
就说那个
earth creatures
地球生物
The situation of growth
生长的情形
It is indeed very
也的确是非常的
special
非常的
how to say
怎么说呢
very prosperous
非常的繁盛
OK
OK
In comparison
比较起来
then someone will say
那就会有人说
since we want
既然我们要
two to four degrees hotter
热个两度到四度
that would have been this
那本来这个
Let's say four thousand years to almost ten thousand years ago
就说四千年到差不多一万年前
It's so hot and so good
也是那么热那么好的话
Then why should we worry about the future
那我们何必担心以后
climate warming
气候暖化
The problem
的问题
it was brought up
这是有人提出来的
And it's actually quite interesting that a
并且事实上也蛮有意思的是一个
a very meaningful topic
一个非常有意义的题目
But before we go on
不过在我们在我继续讲之前
I want to give you a little introduction
我想给大家稍微介绍一下
here of course we are here now
这里当然是我们现在是在这里
OK
OK
Then here it is a logarithm
那这里它这个是一个对数的
this this mark
这个这个作标
10,000 years from here to here
从这里到这里是一万年
So the ancient civilization we are talking about is here
所以我们讲的古文明是在这里
That
那
And then this little iceberg is here
然后这个小冰河奇在这里
OK
OK
The other four big glacial oddities are here
另外这四个大冰河奇在这里
Often the previous ones are many, many, many
往往前的那就更很多很多很多的
big and small glaciers
大大小小的冰河奇
OK
OK
ah
啊
what does this picture mean
这个图有什么意思呢
I'm here to tell you about
我这里就是说要跟大家介绍一下
The flood control by heavy rain was almost 4,000 years ago
大雨治水是差不多四千年前
OK
OK
That's an interesting one here
那个这里是一个蛮有趣的
Today I participated in the one mentioned by Vice President Wang just now
今天我参加那个刚才王副院长提到的那个
Conference on Environmental History of East Asian History
东亚历史的环境历史的conference
Many people mentioned the situation when the heavy rain cured the water
很多人提到大雨治水那时候的情形
Yes, what I mentioned just now is about greenhouse gases
对 刚才我提到的就是说温室气体
What if you assume different greenhouse gases
你假设不同的温室气体的情况下
In the worst case scenario, the greenhouse increases by almost four degrees
最坏的情况下增温室差不多增四度
In the best case, the temperature will increase by nearly 2 degrees.
最好的情况下也增温也将近2度
So 2 degrees to 4 degrees is currently our forecast
所以2度到4度是目前我们预测的
Scenarios for model-predicted warming
模式预测的增温的情形
Going back to the four ancient Wenmin countries we talked about just now
回到刚才我们讲四大温民古国
China Egypt Asia Minor
中国埃及小亚西亚
About 4,000 to 7,000 years ago
距今是差不多4000年到7000年之前
developed at that time
那时候发展出来
Of course we just saw this and that
当然我们刚才看到这个那个
almost all history
几乎所有的历史
Scholars are talking about this
学家在谈这个的
It is said that there was a good climate at that time
都是说那时候有良好的气候环境
but the problem is
可是问题是
What exactly does a good climate environment mean?
良好气候环境到底指的是什么
Most books will say
绝大部分的书都会说
It's very warm in the middle of the northern hemisphere
是北半球中尾度非常温暖
Here I want to tell you
这里我想跟大家讲一下
Wait so everyone can see
等等大家可以看出来
This answer is definitely not like this
这个答案绝对不是这个样子
This is actually the wrong answer
这个其实是错误的答案
I don't agree with the warm climate in the middle of the northern hemisphere
我是不认同北半球中尾度温暖的气候
That is what we just mentioned
也就是刚才我们提到的
This is 4,000 to 10,000 years ago
就是这个4000年到1万年前
this warm climate
这个温暖气候
It is caused by itself to make the climate environment particularly good
本身是造成是使气候环境特别的好
why
为什么呢
Because you speak purely for the warmth of the temperature
因为你讲说纯粹是为了温度的温暖
You can go to lower latitudes to find warmer conditions
大家可以到比较低纬度去找到更温暖的情形
And all the four ancient civilizations developed almost in the middle and high latitudes
而所有的四个古文明它的发展几乎都是在中高纬度
Not to mention the Huaxia people, we chose the Yellow River as the mother river of our so-called civilization
更不要说华夏族我们选了黄河做我们的所谓文明的母亲河
If it is purely for warmth, it can choose the Yangtze River
假如说是纯粹为了温暖它大可以选长江
The Yangtze River is more abundant
长江水还更充沛
So it did not choose the Yangtze River
所以它没选长江
It means that warmth is definitely not the first consideration
就表示说温暖绝对不是第一个考量
Elsewhere we also think warmth isn't really a first consideration
其他地方我们也认为温暖并不是一个真正的第一考量
The reason I mentioned just now is that Lucy
原因我刚才也提到了我们从就是说Lucy
Lucy to people for 3 million years
向向人的Lucy 300万年以来
evolutionary life of man
人类的进化生活
basically living on an earth that is one degree colder than it is now
基本上都是在一个比现在还冷一度的地球上在生活
Because we have long been accustomed to this cool climate
因为我们早就蛮习惯这个凉爽的气候
another one
另外一个
another very important point
另外一个很重要的一点
That is to say, let's look at the cool climate
就是说我们再看凉好的气候环境
what does it mean
它到底是什么意思
The cool climate environment actually includes a wide range of
凉好的气候环境其实包括很广
it actually i think
它其实我是认为
The most important point is to include natural disasters which are relatively rare
最重要的一点是要包括自然的灾害是比较少
When natural disasters are less likely to occur
发生自然灾害的几率比较少的情况下
Only then can it be called a cool climate environment
才可以叫做凉好的气候环境
Everyone assumes to look a little more carefully
大家假说是稍微仔细看一下
The geographic location of the four major civilizations and five ancient countries
四大文明五古国那个地理位置
you all noticed
你都注意到
No country is right next to the sea
没有任何一个国是就在海旁边
And no country is right next to the earthquake zone
也没有任何一个国就在地震带旁边
According to the earthquake zone, the closest one is probably China.
据地震带最近最近的恐怕也就是中国了
It's pretty close according to Japan
据日本还蛮近的
But wait a while and see that the low tide of raising young people is still far from the sea.
可是你等一等看到养少文化下潮都是离海还蛮远的
So the so-called earthquakes and tsunamis had no effect on these ancient civilizations
所以所谓地震跟海啸本来就对这些古文明没有什么影响
But I'm afraid it's also those ancient civilizations that are really influenced by ancient civilizations.
不过恐怕也是真正的古文明有影响的那些古文明
Those close to earthquakes and tsunamis may not have developed
接近地震跟海啸的恐怕都没有发展出来
I believe
我相信
The problem now is that the risk of natural disasters is relatively low
现在问题是自然灾害风险比较低
Floods and droughts I believe are our ancestors
水灾跟汗灾我相信是我们的祖先
and any of their people from ancient civilizations
还有任何的古文明的他们的人
What they worry about most should be the thing they worry about most
他们最担心应该是最担心的事情
flood
水灾
with the drought
跟旱灾
Actually until now
其实一直到现在
Chinese mainland
中国大陆
Speaking of which, of course we are in Taiwan.
讲说是当然说我们台湾了
We in Taiwan are all worried about floods
我们台湾大家担心的都是水灾
best every year
每年最厉害的
The most shocking is the flood
震撼性最大的是水灾
But in mainland China it is a drought
可是在中国大陆却是旱灾
Economic losses from their drought yearly drought
他们旱灾每年旱灾的经济损失
it's a disaster for them
是占他们天灾的
i remember the number
我记得数目
It is almost like this in more than 70% of their natural disasters every year
是在整个他们的天灾的差不多70%以上每年几乎都是这样
so
所以说
How to avoid floods and droughts is actually the most important issue
怎么样避免水灾跟旱灾其实是一个最重要的问题
Let's take China as an example below
我们底下就把用中国做例子来看
that
那个
Yangshao culture is famous
仰少文化很有名的
he is about a.d.
他是差不多公元
three thousand five thousand years ago
三千年五千年之前
Yang Shao Culture
仰少文化
Did you see
大家看到没有
It's quite far away
它这个距离还蛮远的
I'm afraid the tsunami won't reach here
这个海嘯恐怕到不了这边
This is near the Yellow River
这个是在黄河附近
OK
OK
Of course it was 3,000 to 5,000 years ago
这里当然是三千到五千年前
more than a thousand years later
一千多年以后
to the downward position
到了下朝的位置
is here
是在这里
Of course, I didn't want to post this picture.
当然这个图我本来不想放
when i put it in
我放进来的时候
Originally, President Wang Fu was not here to preside over the
本来王复院长还不是来主持
So I boldly put it in
所以我大胆的把它放进来
After he came
结果他来了以后
I have sent it to Mr. Hou
我已经送到侯先生那边去
too late to withdraw
来不及撤了
I know this picture is still a bit worse than his picture standard
我知道这个图跟他那个图标准还是差一些
But there are a lot of interesting things in this picture
不过这个图里面有很多很有意思的东西
did you notice
大家注意到没有
not just down toward him is in this totally in
不只是下朝他是在这个完全在
Yellow River Basin
黄河流域
it
它
Here is the Yellow River
这里显得黄河
it is the modern yellow river
它是现代的黄河
did you notice
大家注意到没有
The Yellow River and the Yangtze River are very different
黄河跟长江很不一样
Yangtze
长江
look
你看
messy little nearby
附近乱七八糟的小小的
look small lake
看起来小湖
They are actually big lakes
其实都是很大的湖
You see the Yellow River is naked
你看黄河光溜溜的
not a single lake
一个湖都没有
it's interesting
这很有意思
until the Qin Dynasty
一直到秦朝
This neighbor of the Qin Dynasty
秦朝的这个邻居
Everyone noticed that the Yellow River is still the main
大家注意到还是黄河为主
the yellow river is here
黄河在这里
OK
OK
this way
这样过去
Or the Yellow River
还是黄河为主
Yangtze river in
长江在
OK
OK
The Yangtze River has just begun to develop
长江刚刚开始开发
It's Qin Dynasty
到秦朝了
So from just now BC
所以从刚才公元前
five thousand years to now
五千年到现在
almost five thousand years
几乎是五千年的时间
Chinese culture has always been
中华文化一直是在
Mainly the Yellow River
以黄河为主
But with the Yellow River as the center
可是以黄河为中心
See how the Yellow River treats the Chinese nation
看看黄河对待中华民族是什么样子
Guide County near Qinghai
在青海附近贵德县
If people don't write this as the Yellow River
假如说人家不把这个写成黄河的话
No matter how I guess, I can't guess that this is the Yellow River
我怎么样猜我也猜不出来这是黄河
Because you see the river is quite clear
因为你看这河水蛮清的
It feels like swimming in summer
都感觉像夏天的时候游泳过去
must be very enjoyable
一定很过瘾的
But here is Qinghai
可是在这个是青海
200 kilometers downstream of it
在它200公里下游
It's Lanzhou
就是蓝洲
Yellow River in Lanzhou
蓝洲的黄河
You see it's yellow
你看就是黄的了
we can see how far it is
我们可以看一看它差多远
The picture of Qinghai is almost here on this machine
青海的那个图是差不多在这个机这里
there here
那里在这里
The blue continent is a little bit above the red dot
蓝洲是在红点上面一点点
So basically only the difference
所以基本上只有差
About two or three hundred kilometers vary
差不多两三百公里不同
So from the clear is
所以就从清的就是
How do you say that is very clean
那个那个怎么说来很很干净的
Do it right away, that is to say
马上办成就是说
I'm totally loess in it
我完全都是黄土在里面
Well, we also have good statistics on this now.
那这个我们现在也有很好的统计
Of course the Yellow River belongs to the Republic of China as we know it now
黄河当然现在是我们知道是我们中华民国的
The Mother of Chinese Culture in the Republic of China and
中华民国中华文化的母亲和
That park was between 5,000 and 2,000 years ago
那个公园前五千到两千年
This has always been here
这个是一直都在这里发展
Actually we just saw
其实我们刚才看到
In fact, until the park
其实一直到到这个公园的时候
When talking about the Warring States Period
就说战国的时候
In the future, the Yellow River will still dominate
以后都还是都还是以黄河为主
for the main place
为主要的地方
as a center
为中心
But we know the historical record
可是我们知道历史记载
Over the past 2,500 years or so
在过去的两千五百年左右
flooding of the yellow river
黄河泛滥
almost 1600 times
差不多1600次
Average 1.6 years
平均1.6年
flood once
就泛滥一次
i think everyone knows
我想大家都知道
Bo Yang
博洋
Bo Yang just said
博洋就说
The Yellow River is like a bird on the ground
黄河像一只在地上
writhing beautiful
翻腾漂亮的
dragon
巨龙
Bring us an irresistible disaster
给我们带来无法抗拒的灾难
If the Yellow River says
黄河假如说
really is
真正本来就是
like this
像这个样子的话
i can't figure it out
我就想不出来
Ancestors of Huaxia
华夏族的祖先
how would you think
怎么会想到
ran to the edge of the Yellow River
跑到黄河边上
to develop that culture
去发展那个文化
I think
我想
he this
他这个
IQ even me
智商 即使是我
Of course, people's IQ has always been
当然人的智商一直在
enhanced
增进的
For example, here my IQ
比如说在这里我的智商
should be relatively low
应该是比较低的
Because everyone looks younger than me
因为大家看起来都比我年轻
The younger generations are indeed
年轻 这个一代一代的确是
This IQ has been increasing
这个智商一直在增加的
but our
可是我们的
Chinese ancestors
华夏的祖先
No matter how low your IQ is, it won't be that low.
智商再低也不会低到那种程度
Let's say there is a big flood every year and a half
就说每一年半来一次大水
you are still there
你还在那里
develop your culture
发展你的文化
This is very, very unreasonable
这个是非常非常不合理的事情
so i thought
所以我就想
When I was speaking this time, I thought
在这一次讲的时候我就想
I want to discuss this issue with you.
我想把这个问题好好跟大家讨论一下
look
你看
We saw
我们看到
That is to say, the Yellow River was long ago
就是说黄河在很早之前
5000 BC 2000 years ago
公元前5000 2000年前
temperature we see
气温我们看到了
2 degrees C beyond the present
超出现在2度C
This is absolutely proven
这个是绝对有证明的
over there
在那里
That is to say, digging out
就是说在挖出来的
have dug this fish
有挖到这个鱼
have dug this rhino
有挖到这个犀牛
These are more tropical animals.
这都是比较热带才有的动物
So the temperature at that time
所以那时候的温度
The guess should be the guess should be no problem
的猜测应当是推测应当是没有什么问题的
The loess soil was originally very fertile.
黄土这个土质本来是非常肥沃
easy to do
跟做起来非常容易
So at that time, there were actually many, many
所以那时候其实是很多很多有
favorable conditions
优厚的条件
In addition, they mentioned that there is a saying in this ancient book
另外他们提到这个古书上有讲
There are many large lakes in the middle and lower reaches of the Yellow River
黄河中下游有很多大湖
Just now I told you that there is no lake now
刚才我跟大家讲现在现在没有湖了
At that time many great lakes
那时候很多大湖
Let's just say that the existence of the Great Lakes proves that
我们就说大湖的存在证明当时
The Yellow River carries very little sediment
黄河夹带泥沙很少
If there is a lot of sand
假如说是泥沙非常多
as now
像现在一样
any kind of lake
无论什么样的湖
will be pre-qualified in a few years
几年之内就会被预赛的
So it shows that I was super late for this sentence at that time.
所以显示当时这句话我是超来的
He said it showed that there was less rainstorm at that time
他说显示当时暴雨少
I said I've been raining for so long
我说我做了这么久暴雨
How dare someone tell me
居然有人敢跟我说
At that time the rainstorm was small
当时暴雨小
so it's very difficult
所以都是非常难
But his guess is very reasonable.
不过他这个猜测很有道理的
Because at that time since there was very little sediment
因为那时候既然是很少泥沙
His torrential rain should be rare
他这个暴雨应当是很少的
Forest and grassland are all in good condition
森林草原直批都是都是很好的情形
That is to say at that time
也就是说在那个时候
I guess the Yellow River is clear
我猜啊黄河是清的了
Of course when I write this clearly
那当然我这个写清的时候
This is also far
这也是远在
I know that our Vice President Wang is going to host
我知道我们这个王副院长要来主持
So I don't know if he will say later
所以我不曉得他待会会不会说
You have a problem with this
你这个这个很有问题啊
But this thing
不过这个这个东西
I believe this my past ah
我相信这个我这个过去的啊
Actually, it was actually when the Five Brothers of the Han Dynasty
实际啊实际是汉汉五弟的时候
That that was already in AD there
那个那个原在那已经是公元
After AD, it is written in the whole article.
公元后的啊写的全篇里面啊
He doesn't have the name Huang He
他没有黄河这个名字
And the river at that time was the Yellow River at that time
而那时候的河啊是那时候的黄河
Collectively called the river, not the Yellow River
统称叫做河不叫黄河
So it is likely that even when performing
所以很可能即使在使绩的时候
This Yellow River may be a little yellow
这黄河可能有点黄
But definitely not as yellow as today
可是绝对不像今天那么黄
OK
OK
So this seems to make sense
所以这个看起来是有点道理
except this
除了这个之外
We actually had a recent
我们其实有一个最近
Ours is also why I put this
我们这个也是我为什么把这个
The reason this little history is here
这小段历史放在这里的原因
Some of our recent research
我们最近的做的一些研究
sorry
对不起
I must have been pressing this thing
我一定是一直按这个东西
it doesn't work
它这个又不行
back to the original
回到这个原来的
We did a recent study
我们做最近的做的一个研究
That is to say, when the sea temperature in the tropics is relatively low,
就是说热带海温比较低的时候
in this case
在这种情况下
Global rainfall intensity will decrease
全球的降雨强度会降低
That is to say, the rainstorm will decrease
也就是说暴雨会减少
And light rain is relatively less
而中小雨相对减多
in this case
在这种情况下
It will provide more favorable rainfall conditions for Nongmu
会提供对浓穆比较有利的降雨条件
This is an estimate we made
这个是我们做的一个估计
what does this picture represent
这个图代表什么呢
That is, we calculate the rainfall intensity
就是我们算降雨强度
With low pseudo-degrees is the change in tropical ocean temperature
随着低伪度就是热带海洋温度的变化
The intensity of the rainfall is here
降雨强度在这边
Divide the global rainfall into 10 equal parts
就是把全球的降雨分成10等分
The strongest rainfall is here
最强的降雨在这边
Minimal rainfall is here
最小的降雨在这边
That 10 is the top 10% of heavy rainfall
那10就是前10%的强降雨
Did you see
大家看到没有
If you increase the sea temperature by one degree
你假设把海温增加一度
Its heavy rainfall will increase by almost 100%
它强降雨就增加差不多一整倍100%
You think the sea temperature at that time was cooler
你把当时的海温是比较凉
if it's cold
凉一度的话
In other words, the heavy rainfall should be smaller than the current
也就是说强降雨会应当是比目前小
almost double
差不多一整倍
This means that at that time in the Yellow River Basin
这个也就是说当时在黄河流域
The rain at that time was the kind of torrential rain.
那时候的雨是那种暴雨比较少
much less than now
少很多比现在少很多
but light rain
可是中小雨
light rain it will increase if it is cold
中小雨 它冷的话它会增加
Here is the temperature increase it decreases
这里是温度增加 它减少
it increases when it is cold
冷的时候它会增加
Moderate rain will increase
中小雨会增加
So we all know that heavy rain is of course related to floods and landslides
所以我们都知道大雨当然是跟水灾土石流有关系
So you reduce the risk of this flood
所以你减少了这种水灾的风险
Moderate rain increases
中小雨增加
Moderate rain is an important moisture to keep the soil moist
中小雨是保持土壤湿润的重要水分
It is also an important oxygen-containing edge for groundwater
也是地下水的重要的含氧的缘
Therefore, the increase of light rain can reduce sweating in
所以中小雨的增加可以减少汗在
And it is very beneficial to the maintenance of deep drench and straight back
并且有非常有利深淋直背的保育
I make a picture here
我这里做一个图
Basically, it means that the tropical sea temperature is low
基本上就是说热带海温脚低的话
The intensity of the rainfall will decrease
降雨的强度会降低
Light rain will increase, heavy rain will decrease
小雨增多 大雨会减少
Of course, to use an old saying, it means good weather
当然套一句老话就是风调雨顺
in this case
在这种情况下
The existence of creatures and lakes becomes possible
生灵跟湖泊它的存在就变得可能
That is to say, the Yellow River was not yellow at that time.
也就是说黄河当时不黄
Actually it makes sense
其实是有它的道理的
In terms of weather
从气象方面来说
The temperature of the original ocean
当初的海洋的温度
The ocean is cooler
海洋的温度比较低
OK Ocean temperatures at lower latitudes are cooler
OK 低纬度的海洋温度比较低
this is a very important factor
这是一个非常重要的因素
We are thinking that reducing the intensity
我们是认为使降于强度降低
Then make soil and water conservation in the Yellow River Basin easier
然后使黄河流域水土保持比较容易
That is to say, in the Yellow River Basin
也就是说在黄河流域
That is to say, during this period
就是说在这个多时期
Gongyuan from 2000 to 5000 years
工源2000到5000年那个时间
we can know
我们是可以知道
this is fertile soil
这个是土壤肥沃
forest lake
森林湖泊
very many
很非常多
good weather
风调雨顺
Yellow River becomes very reliable
黄河变得非常可靠
No
不
Definitely not a flood every 1.6 years
绝对不是每1.6年就发生一次洪水
I just said it
刚才也讲了
The temperature is relatively mild
气温也相对的温和
This will become the kiln basket of Chinese culture
这个才会变成华夏文化的窑篮
will also
也会
that is
就是说
this is what i think
这是我认为
Why was the Yellow River chosen as the mother river of Chinese culture?
为什么黄河当初会被选为华夏文化的母亲河
Here I mentioned heavy rain water control
这里我提到了大雨治水
That's what I'm talking about here
我这里是这么讲的
I said
我说
For example, in 2000 BC
假如说工源前2000年的时候
Also every 1.6 years on average
也是平均1.6年一次
Everyone
大家
You can figure it out
一算就可以算出来
He cured the water for 13 years
他治水13年
did not come home three times
三次都没有回家
Did not go home three times
三次三国家门没回家
it is known
我们都知道
this 13 years
这个13年之间
He should flood 8 times
他应当泛滥8次
ok
ok
on basic statistics
就基本的统计
that flooded 8 times
那泛滥8次
Think about it
你想想
No matter how hard you rain
你大雨再厉害
But of course he succeeded
可是他当然是成功了
he his father failed
他他他父亲没成功
Everyone knows what the consequences are
大家都知道后果是什么
then he succeeded
那他成功了
Is it really raining in the past
难道真的大雨在过去
It is really better than the past 2000
真的是比过去2000
Let's just say that the next 2500 years
就说他以后的2500年
The Yellow River floods all day long
那个黄河一天到晚泛滥
The Yellow River has this all day long
那黄河一天到晚有这个
dedicated person
专门的人
smart man engineer
聪明的人工程师
to control the Yellow River
去治理黄河
bad governance
都治理不好
and he
而他
You see heavy rain for 13 years
你看大雨13年
but all succeeded
却都成功
so so i say
所以所以我说
This is Holland Green
這個荷蘭綠來算
I believe this is not true
我相信這個不是事實
but i was guessing
而是我在猜的
My answer is to say
我這個答案就是說
Within 13 years of heavy rain and stagnant water
大雨滯水13年內
like we just said
就像我們剛才講的
good weather basically
風調雨順基本上
Of course there are occasional small floods
當然偶然免不了有一些小型的氾濫
maybe once or twice
可能一兩次
that it this
那它的這個
and high technology
又有很高的技術
then try very hard
然後又非常努力
once or twice, of course
一兩次當然順利
it passed
順利就過去了
I also think it's the right time and place
我也認為是天時地利
all helped it
都幫了它忙
Of course it won't work if it doesn't work hard
當然它自己不努力也不行
But the so-called heavy rain
不過所謂言之大雨
It should be mostly its luck
應該是大部分是它的運氣
i'm guessing
我在猜
instead of saying its 13 years
而不是說它13年
it's really governed so well
它真正治理得那麼好
suppose it's that powerful
假說它那麼厲害
and it that method
並且它那個方法
I also know later
後來也都知道了
next 2500 years
以後的2500年
that is to say those people
那就是說那些人
such a smart person
那麼聰明的人
There should be a way
應當有辦法
governance success
治理成功
so i believe
所以我相信
From this logic
从这种逻辑来说
indeed in
的确在
that is
就是说
When ancient civilizations developed
古文明发展的时候
that
那个
at that time
那时候的
Climatic conditions
气候条件
That is to say, the conditions of rainfall
也就是说降雨的条件
is far better than
是远比
far than
远比
that is
就是说
past
过去
over 2000 years
2000多年来的
well done
来的好
then finish the story
那讲完这个故事
everyone is fine
大家也没有问题
here
这里
because I can't wait
因为我等一等不回来
tell these historical things
讲这些历史的事情
if there is a problem
假如有问题
can now bring it up
现在可以提出来
Then we seem to have quite a long time today
那我们今天好像时间也蛮长的
seems to be every time
好像是每次
ah
啊
right
对
have a lot of time
有有不少的时间
so everyone has a problem
所以大家有问题
mention at any time
随时提
ah
呀
i think this is very
我想这个非常
very interesting
非常有意思
hear the story
听到这故事
that's in
那可是在
The Yangtze River We know that the Yangtze River was 50 or 60 years ago
長江我們知道長江在五六十年以前
It was clear before
之前也都是清的
Clear and without yellow sand
清澈的也是沒有黃沙的
but now
可是現在的話
It's like turning into the Yellow River
也都是變成黃河一樣
the main reason
那這個主要原因
Of course it's because of the development
當然是因為是開發的關係
Cut down the upper forest
把上游的森林都砍掉了
and then developed a variety of uses
然後開發了各種的使用
So resulting in the current
所以造成了現在的
The Yangtze River is also changing
這個長江也變一變一變
So this of course this could be
所以這個當然這可能是
because time is short
因為時間很短
this big change happened
就發生這大改變
Maybe it's not about the climate
可能不是氣候的關係
Then the change in the Yellow River changes from clear to yellow
那麼在黃河的變由清變成黃
Is it also because of the impact of development?
會不會也是因為有開發的影響
i think it's right
我想這是對的
That is to say, from clear to yellow
就是說從清變黃
It's not just natural reasons
照說不只是天然的原因
that natural cause i believe
那個天然的原因我相信
indeed there are
的確是有的
The climate is changing
這個氣候是有變的
OK
OK
The reason may be more important
原因说不定是更重要
you talk
你讲说
Ask me if the Yellow River is really turning yellow because of man-made
问我这黄河真正变黄是人为的原因
or natural reasons
还是自然的原因
I believe that although I would like to have
我相信虽然我会想都有
However, there should be more human reasons
不过人为的原因应当是比较多的
Population after the Warring States Period
战国以后人口
not after the Warring States Period
不是战国以后
After the Qing Dynasty
清朝以后
The population is increasing very fast
这人口增加的是非常的快
Especially when the country begins to unify
尤其国家开始统一
start getting bigger
开始越来越大
growing population
人口越来越多
Lin Kan speaks very, very fast
森林侃发得非常非常快
Soil and water conservation is more difficult
水土的保持是比较困难的
but i can say
不过我倒可以这么说
Even the Yellow River
即使黄河
We're going back now to keep it hydrated
我们现在去回去保持它的水土
it can actually recover to
它能能真正恢复到
That is to say, the coverage of forest and grassland is everywhere.
就说到处都是森林草原的这种覆盖
i actually have
我其实是有
because of its climate now
因为它的气候现在来说
very unsuitable
非常不适合
This is my forest and grassland
這種就是我森林跟草原的
that's my kind of coverage
就是我那種覆蓋
yes no more questions yet
對 還沒有其他問題
so no words
這樣沒有的話
I think I will introduce to you
我想我底下給大家介紹
That means returning
那個就是說回歸的
Back to the question we started to talk about today
回到今天開始要談的問題
That is to say spring and autumn warming
也就是說春秋暖化
Impact on Taiwan
對我們臺灣的影響
before speaking
在講之前
I thought I'd better introduce
我想我還是要跟大家介紹一下
What is the difference between weather and climate
天氣跟氣候有什麼不同
because it is often misunderstood
因為常常被誤解
Look at the weather in general
你看天氣一般來說
I am a more general definition
我是一個比較籠統的定義
In fact, there is no very strict definition
其實也沒有非常嚴格的定義
Generally the weather is
一般來說天氣就是
The short-term state and change of the air
空氣短期的狀態與變化
In the short term we generally
短期我們一般
say within 10 days
就说差不多10天以内
Basically within 10 days
10天以内基本上
why use 10 days
为什么用10天
The main thing is that we now
主要也是说我们现在
best weather forecaster
最好的天气预报员
Basically can only predict 10 days
基本上只能预测10天
10 days later
10天以后
Talking about the weather is useless
讲天气也白大
The weather you guessed, the weather he told
你猜的天气跟他讲的天气
exactly the same
一模一样
It's all 50% right and 50% wrong
都是50%对50%错
so this we mean the weather
所以这个我们是说天气
That example is what the temperature will be tomorrow
那例子就是明天温度是如何
The weather today is bad
今天天气不好
the climate is very different
气候就很不一样
Climate is the long-term average of weather
气候是天气的长期平均
This long term has a certain definition
这个长期是有一个一定的定义的
World Meteorological Organization definition
世界气象组织定义
long term is 30 years
长期是30年
That means you have 30 years of data
也就是说你有30年的资料
you are qualified to say
你才有资格说
I have a climate value for this
我这个有一个气候值
For example, if we say that the global average
假如说比如说我们说全球平均
The temperature is 15 degrees
气温是15度
That means we at least have a past
那就表示说我们至少有过去
30 years of data
30年的资料
to average out this 15 degrees
来平均得到这个15度
Of course we have hundreds of years of data
我们当然有上百年的资料
How many typhoons come to Taiwan every year
每年有多少台风来台
We've certainly had good weather this year
今年我们当然是风调雨顺
lucky only one
运气不错 只有一个
But does anyone know how many typhoons we have on average?
可是有没有人知道我们平均有几个台风
does anyone have a guess
有没有人要猜的
alone air does not count
独大气的不算
seven
七个
no one has to guess
没人要猜
We have an average of four typhoons a year
我们一年平均有四个台风
Qingtai
清台
There is also a definition
也有个定义的
What is typhoon Qingtai?
台风清台是什么来的
The Bureau of Meteorology issued a warning on the road.
气象局发布路上警报就算了
Even before it arrived in Taiwan
它即使到了台湾之前
It's okay to turn a corner and walk away
拐个弯走掉那也算
continue
继续
you are not there yet
你还不在
Won't
不会
I you are moving
我 你在动
it's gonna be the last chance
it's gonna be the last chance
There are almost four a year
是一年有差不多四个
We only have one this year
今年我们只有一个来
it was better for us then
那时对我们比较好
and additionally
并且另外来说
typhoon four typhoon
台风四个台风
An average of four typhoons a year
平均一年四个台风
It brings us almost 40 percent of our rainfall
它带给我们差不多百分之四十的雨量
So if you say that it is a good thing that the typhoon does not come
所以大家假如说是认为台风不来是好事
that's totally wrong
那是完全错了
It's a bad thing if the typhoon doesn't come
台风不来其实是坏事
If none of the four typhoons comes
你假如台风四个台风都不来的话
Forty percent of our annual rain is gone
我们一年百分之四十的雨就不见了
60% left
剩百分之六十
The second year of spring plowing guarantees that you can do nothing
第二年的春耕保证你没有办法
In fact, this year we can say that luck is the best.
今年其实我们可以说运气算最好了
Several typhoons are coming
好几个台风要来不来
just wipe it on the side
就在旁边擦过去
bring us a lot of rain
给我们带来不少的雨
I still remember when the first typhoon came
我还记得第一个台风来的时候
Seems like we were heading for a drought
好像我们那时候正要旱灾
Then there is a typhoon coming
那这个有个台风来变得
become rainy
变得风跳雨顺
There are several typhoons this year
今年有好几个台风都是差边过
that said it brought the rain
那就说带来了雨
But it didn't bring anything special, just more rain
却没有带来非常就说更大了雨
Of course there will be disasters
那当然是会有灾害的
After we make this definition
我们做这个定义以后
Many questions we can understand very quickly
很多问题我们就可以很快就了解
because the media often say
因为媒体常常说
Just like there were several weather events in previous winters
好比从前冬天有几次天气事件
very heavy snow and cold
非常大的风雪跟酷寒
Then some media said
那就有媒体说
Are we going into Xiaoice and Qi?
我们是不是要进入小冰和旗
Everyone knows this definition
这个大家假知道这个定义
Xiaobing and the flag are hundreds of years old
小冰和旗它是几百年
one or two hundred years
一两百年
its a climate event
它是一个气候事件
This is a few weather events
这个是几次天气事件
two are not the same
两个根本不是一回事
So of course it doesn't mean
所以当然不表示
In addition, this particular event
另外也就说这种特殊性的事件
Morakot European heatwave
莫拉克 欧洲热浪
Said to be caused by climate warming
说是气候暖化造成的
Why
为什么
Because this is still a few weather events
因为这个还是一个几次天气事件
And climate warming is a climate problem
而气候暖化是一个气候的问题
Even without climate warming
即使没有气候暖化
We also know that typhoons like Morakot
我们也知道像摩拉克这种台风
There is still a chance to come to Taiwan
来台湾的机会还是有
not no
并不是没有
OK
OK
africa europe heatwave
非洲的欧洲的热浪
There is also a chance
来的机会也是有
it's not without
它并不是没有的
but what can we say
可是我们可以怎么说
in the context of climate warming
在气候暖化的情况下
I'll show you here
这里我给大家看
We used to be in Taiwan
我们台湾过去
Analyze data from 1961 to 2005
从1961年到2005年的数据来分析
Do an average every 10 years
每10年做一个平均
Then do an analysis of rainfall intensity
然后做降雨强度的一个分析
here is heavy rain
这边是强降雨
This is cat cat rain
这边是猫猫雨
OK
OK
On average, people can see different colors every ten years
每十年平均大家可以看不同颜色
The most recent is only five years
最近的是只有五年
2001 to 2005
2001到2005
You can see that heavy rainfall is increasing
大家可以看到强降雨在增加
With the age because it is getting hotter
随年代因为越来越热
OK increases with temperature
OK 随温度而增加
While light rain decreases with temperature
而中小雨随温度而减少
very obvious
非常明显
For Typhoon Morakot
对莫拉克台风来说
This picture makes sense
这个图就很有意义了
Everyone noticed that the average rainfall in Morakot
大家注意到莫拉克的平均的降雨量
It's about 40 mm per hour
是差不多每小时是差不多40个mm
40 kilometers
40公里
40 kilometers per hour
每小时40公里
rain like this
像这样的降雨
Between 1961 and 1970
在1961年到1970年
You see, it is almost equal to non-existence
你看几乎等于不大存在的
But after 45 years
可是过了45年以后
You can see that it has increased by almost
你看它增加了有差不多
at least three times
至少有三倍
then you can
那你就可以
so to speak
這麼來說
Of course, what I'm talking about now is more general.
當然現在講的還是比較大致上講一點
That is to say
也就是說
Morakot
莫拉克
rain like this typhoon Morakot
像這種莫拉克颱風這種降雨
now than before
現在比從前
Its thirst rate increased
它那個渴然率增加了
and increased considerably
並且增加的相當大
possibly several times
可能有好幾倍
So from this point of view
所以從這個觀點來說
we can talk
我們是可以來談
That is, this single event
就是說這種單一事件
relationship with climate warming
跟氣候暖化的關係
Speaking of climate warming, of course
當然講到氣候暖化
We still have to introduce the greenhouse effect
我們還是得介紹一下溫室效應
greenhouse effect
溫室效應
The most obvious greenhouse effect
最明顯的溫室效應
that is
就是說
If there were no greenhouse gases
假如沒有溫室氣體的話
average temperature of our planet
我們地球的平均溫度
It should be minus 19 degrees
應該是負19度
It is easy to calculate it with the formula of physics
這個很容易用物理的公式把它算出來
but we are now
可是我們現在
just now we saw
剛才我們看到了
The global average temperature is 15 degrees
全球平均溫度15度
So the greenhouse gas greenhouse effect
所以溫室氣體溫室效應
gives us 34 degrees
給了我們34度
that is
就是說
very high temperature
非常多 非常高的温度
The main greenhouse gases of the earth are as follows:
地球的主要的温室气体有下类几种
Among them, what everyone often hears is Jiawan, which loves to raise carbon dioxide.
其中大家常常听到的都是爱养化碳的甲丸
less commonly heard is water vapor
不常听到的是水蒸气
Water vapor is actually one of the most important greenhouse gases
水蒸气其实是一个最重要的温室气体
It says it's inside 34 degrees
它就说在34度里面
its very rough estimate
它非常的粗略的估计
it accounts for at least half
它占至少有一半
It occupies half because of water
它占有一半是因为水的关系
water vapor relationship
水蒸气的关系
Others are relatively few
其他相对来说是比较少的
But why don't we hear the water
可是为什么我们不听到水呢
Because mainly water is not affected by water in the air
因为主要是水不受到空气中的水
unaffected by human activities
到现在不受人类的活动的影响
so we got lucky
所以我们运气不错
water untouched by us
水没有受到我们的影响
If it is really influenced by us
假如真受到我们的影响
that's really
那真得是
it's a big deal
是不得了的事情
But these other
可是其他的這些
Ozone
暗氧化碳甲丸臭氧
effector
效器
are all affected by human activities
全都受到人類活動的影響
and have now increased a lot
並且現在都增加了很多
Especially the armor pill increased
尤其是甲丸增加了
I'm afraid there are three times
恐怕有三倍
tripled
增加了三倍
The others are also adding considerable numbers
其他的也都是增加相當可觀的數字
we can see here
我們在這裡可以看到
You see when Komaru starts here
你看甲丸從這裡開始的時候
Kamaru is here
甲丸在這裡
It was only less than 600
本來只有差不多600都不到
How much has it increased now
現在已經增加到多少
almost 2000
將近2000了
nearly quadrupled
將近四倍了甲丸
dark carbon dioxide increase
暗氧化碳增加
are also very obvious
也都是非常明顯
effector increased significantly
效器增加非常明顯
This is the year 2000
這個是公元2000年
this
這個
right
對
This is web recovery
這個是網恢復
Push is 2000 years ago is here
推是2000年前是在这里
Of course everyone will say
当然大家会说
we have everything to cool now
我们现在有一切可以凉
How did this get cold?
这个到底怎么凉出来的
Does anyone know this
这个有没有人知道
no one dozed off
都没人打瞌睡
so i ask the question
所以我问问题
smile is not big
笑容也不大了
sometimes someone dozes off
有时候有人打瞌睡
I asked him
我一问他
he woke up immediately
他立刻惊醒
this is very effective
这个是很有效
Everyone seems to be paying attention today
今天好像大家都还蛮注意的
this thing like this currently
这个东西像这种目前
In fact, it is also a method that has only recently begun to be discovered.
其实也都是最近近代才开始发现的方法
I remember it was in the 70s that I started to know how to cool
我记得是70年代才开始知道怎么凉
That is to say, the Greenland or Antarctic
这就是说把格林兰的或者说南极的
his ice
他那个冰
Hit one to knock down that icicle
打一个把那个冰柱打下来
call up
打上来
Drill down and pull that icicle out
钻下来把那个冰柱拉出来
its icicles
它的冰柱
Especially the icicles in Antarctica
尤其是南极的冰柱
Antarctic snowfall is very slow
南极降雪非常慢
Icicles are formed from what would have been snow
冰柱的形成是本来是雪
The snow pressure of snow pressure will be there in the future
雪压的雪压就有了以后
crushed into ice
就压成冰了
OK
OK
when pressed into ice
压成冰的时候
Everyone knows that between snow and snow
大家知道雪跟雪之间
it has bubbles
它有气泡的了
that bubble it is preserved
那个气泡它被保留下来
that little bubble
那个小小的气泡
ice bubbles
冰的小小的气泡
you are deeper
你是越深的
Of course the longer the history
当然是历史越久
You take those air bubbles out of the ice
你把那些气泡把冰拿出来
take the air bubbles out
把里面的气泡拿出来
There are bubbles in there
那里面气泡含有的
Carbon dioxide can cool down
二氧化碳可以凉出来
That's carbon dioxide
那就是当时的二氧化碳
Now we can put this
现在我们可以把这个
Just say ice core
就说冰冰芯
This can always be done
这个可以一直做到
Almost almost a million years ago
将近将近很接近一百万年了
already
现在已经
so say
所以就说
Of course, only about
当然目前只做到差不多
400,000 years around 500,000 years
40万年 50万年左右
But there is hope to see
不过以后是有希望可以看到
How much carbonized carbon was there 1 million years ago
100万年前的二人化碳有多少
The effect of greenhouse gases on the temperature of the world
温室气体对世界上的温度影响
The most obvious and best example is this graph
最明显的最好的例子就是这个图
OK this picture is also currently
OK这个图也是目前
just say
就说
Speaking of the current temperature increase
讲目前温度增加
Mainly man-made greenhouse gases
主要是人为放出来的温室气体的
the result of the greenhouse effect of that effect
那个效应的温室效应的结果
most important one argument
最重要的一个一个论点
what is this
这个是什么
The black line represents
黑的这条线是代表
Past observed temperature global
过去观测到的温度全球
average change in temperature
溫度平均的變化
What about the blue line?
那藍的線呢
The blue one is not a line
藍的這個這個不算線
What about the blue one?
藍的這一片呢
It means using this climate model
是說用這個氣候的模式
take this increase in greenhouse gases
把這個溫室氣體的增加
It is entirely assumed that there is no increase
完全假設沒有增加
Greenhouse gas assumptions have not changed at all
溫室氣體假設完全沒有變化
calculated global temperature
算出來的全球的溫度
What about the purple one?
那紫色的呢
That is to say, the increase of this greenhouse gas
就是說把這個溫室氣體的增加
it's that influence put in
它的它的那個影響放進去
The results obtained
得到的結果
everyone can see
大家可以看到
observed temperature
觀測到的溫度
is related to this greenhouse gas
是跟這個有溫室氣體
This degree of mildness is quite high
這個溫和的程度是相當的高
Of course everyone also noticed
當然大家也注意到
Here's something that doesn't match
這裡有一個東西並不吻合
Doesn't match any pattern
無論是什麼模式都不吻合
That means
那這也代表就是說
our climate change
我們我們對這個氣候的變化
Although speaking now
雖然說到現在來說
Efforts over the past few decades have made great progress
过去几十年的努力进步很大
But there are still some places we don't know very well
可是我们还是有些地方并不是很清楚
What is the real reason for the temperature change
温度的变化它真正的原因是什么
It is still a point of contention that everyone pays attention to.
到现在还是一个非常大家注意的争论点
This graph is for the most important climate changes observed in the past
这个图是给把过去观测到了最重要的气候变化
As a result, it is always a relatively small section.
结果做一个总比较小节了
The temperature change just above
上面的刚才温度的变化
Temperature changes from the beginning of the thermometer almost 1850
温度变化从有温度计开始差不多1850年
still have a thermometer
还是有温度计
This is the increase in global temperature
这个是全球温度的增加
The thing I just talked about is here
刚才讲的那个东西在这里
The second graph is sea level rise
第二个图是海平面上升
Sea-level rise
海平面上升
This rising 100-year phenomenon
这个上升100年现象
Let's say linear from 1900 to 2000
就说1900年到2000年线性的
The value is almost 0.6 degrees
值是差不多0.6度
If you use linear to measure sea level
海平面你假如用线性的去量测
Its increase is almost 15 cm
它的增加是差不多15公分
15 cm is not very high
15公分不是很高
actually
其实
This image shows snow cover in the northern hemisphere
这个图是北半球的雪的覆盖
Let's talk about this when we have time
那这个我们有时间我们再讲
Although this is more time today
这个虽然说今天的时间比较多
Or let me see when I speak at 7 o'clock
还是我看我什么时候讲7点钟讲
It's almost 50 minutes now
现在差不多50分钟了
ah i remember
啊我记得是
supposedly 90 minutes
supposedly 90分钟
within 90 minutes
90分钟以内
OK, 40 minutes left
OK还剩40分钟
ah
啊
Just now
刚才
we see the temperature increase
我們看到的溫度增加
is here
是在這裡
That is to say, the part with the red line
就是說有紅線的部分
ok
ok
Set it here
放在這裡
This picture is from the past 2000 years
這個圖是過去2000年
Ours is now in 2000
我們這個是2000年是現
That means 11 years ago here in 2000
就是說11年前在這裡2000年
The average global temperature over the past 1000 years
那過去1000年的全球平均氣溫的
picture of
的圖
ok, the part with red line means we have
ok 有紅線的部分是代表我們有
There are real instruments to measure the results
有有真正的儀器量到的結果
I just saw what you saw
就是剛才看大家看的
just now everyone saw
只是剛剛才大家看的
Make this and that coordinate very large
把這個那個坐標拉得很大
That coordinates are squeezed here
那個坐標擠在這裡
You see 1900 is here
你看1900是在這裡
that is here
那個是在這裡
The pattern I just talked about
剛才我講的那個模式
There's no way to grind your little feet up here
沒有辦法磨你的那個那個小腳在這裡
ok
ok
So this is the red part is modern
所以這個是紅色部分是近代的
that front
那前面
Almost 900 years have been made by other methods
差不多九百年都是用其他方法弄出来的
these other ways to get out
这些其他方法弄出来
I believe
我相信
I don't want to ask
我不想该不该问
Does anyone know of any other methods that are most commonly used
有没有人知道其他方法是最常用的其他方法
Other methods most commonly used
最常用的其他方法
In fact, we have a lot of them in Taiwan.
其实是我们台湾蛮多的
That is to say, there is a lot of information
就是说有很多的资料的
But I haven't entered the picture yet.
可是到现在都还没有进到这个图里面
That is to say, the annual rings of the tree
就是说用树的年轮
Tree rings are a very important
树年轮是一个非常重要的
can be used for you to see we also know a lot about trees
可以用来你看我们也知道树的很多
Trees in Taiwan are thousands of years old
台湾的树是好几千年的
So the tree rings give us a lot of data
所以树的年轮给我们不少的data
In addition, of course the refrigerator I just mentioned
另外当然我刚才讲的冰箱
It is the kind of data for higher latitudes
它是给比较高纬度的那种data
In addition there are some data
另外还有一些data
actually use this rock
其实是用这个岩石
Rock because it conducts heat very slowly
岩石因为它导热非常的慢
after you drill it down
你把它钻下去以后
its past temperature
它过去的温度
temperature at the depth of the rock
在岩石的深度的温度
It can be obtained from the previous temperature
可以从前的温度把它求出来
So here are some so-called alternative materials
所以这里都是所谓的替代的一些资料
made out of
所弄出来的
You can also see the uncertainty of modern times
大家也可以看到近代的不定性
gray part
灰色的部分
The gray part gets bigger the farther you go
越往前的灰色部分越大
The greater the uncertainty
不定性越大
But you can also notice
不过大家也可以注意到
This thing still looks pretty sophisticated
这个东西看起来还是相当精密的
because you look at 0.5 degrees
因为你看0.5度
is so big
是这么大
So this looks pretty useful
所以这个看起来还是蛮有用的
correct
对了
But of course this means
不过当然这个的意思
Said to say the past
表示说过去
one thousand years
一千年
The temperature basically does not change much
温度基本上没有太大的变化
Although a little less
虽然有一点点减少
But this reduced value
可是这个减少的值
Just around 0.1 0.2 degrees
只是在0.1 0.2度左右
And this 100 years
而这个100年来
Suddenly increased by 0.6 degrees
一下子增加了0.6度
So this shows more
所以这个更表示出
In other words, the unusualness of this temperature increase
就说这个温度增加的不平常性
That also means that it is more likely
那也表示说这个更可能
most likely caused by human activities
非常可能是人类的活动造成的
Almost everything I just said has been observed in the past.
刚才讲的几乎都是过去观测到的
that climate change
那个气候变化
Climate Change in the 21st Century
21世纪的气候变化
of course we have nothing
当然我们没有什么
no observational data
没有观测的资料
only by this mode
只能靠这个模式
that pattern
那模式
Predicting the 21st Century
预测21世纪
Global warming is 3 to 6 times that of the 20th century
全球增温是20世纪的3到6倍
3 to 6 times of 0.6 is almost 1.8
0.6的3到6倍差不多1.8
That is to say, 2 degrees to 4 degrees
也就是说2度到4度
I told you when I started
我开始的时候就跟大家讲
There are about 2 degrees to 4 degrees
有差不多2度到4度
What about greenhouse gases
看温室气体的情况怎么样
Sea level rise is basically 20 cm to 60 cm
海平面上升基本上是20公分到60公分
The media often say 4 to 8 meters
媒体经常说4到8公尺
And then said that Taipei is gone
然后又说台北不见了
Kaohsiung is gone
高雄不见了
I can type this question, I really want to ask
这个问题我可以我打真正想问一下
hands up
大家举起手
A few people saw the government's 2 degrees C
几个人看了政府2度C了
i'm quite a lot
我相当不少
nearly half
有将近一半
The government's 2 degrees C should have a positive effect on adults
政府2度C对成年来说应当是一个正的效应
I've heard it's often
对这个我听说经常是
Even primary schools have to go to see the government 2 degrees C
连小学都有都有去看政府2度C
middle school let alone
中学更不用说
The government's second-degree district almost sees it every day
政府二度区几乎每般都看
Then I think it should be harmful to them
那我是认为对他们来说应该是有害处的
why come
为什么来
Because of the government's second-degree zone although it has many positive effects
因为政府二度区尽管它有很多正面的效果
He said when you miss his handprint
他就说你想他手印的时候
Dean Wuyue has all gone
五岳院长全都去了
i was invited
我被邀请了
But my position is far behind
可是我那个位置是在很后面
very back
很后面
that
那个
but
不过
this
这个
Ms. Chen Wenqian actually ran up to shake hands
陈文倩小姐居然还跑上来握了手
but that's no use
不过那也没用
I wrote one the next day
我第二天就写了一篇
not the next day
不是第二天
On the third day, I wrote an article saying
第三天那样子就写了一篇说
why there
为什么那里面
most important
绝大部分重要的
The information is actually wrong
资讯其实都是有错误的
The most important information in it is
它里面最重要的资讯就说
With me
跟我
I said hear this
我就说听到这个
he spoke
他讲了
That means the sea level will rise six meters
就是说海平面要上升六公尺
Then it is said that it is likely to rise by 6 meters in 2035
然后是说很可能2035年就上升六公尺
I'll just say you hypothetically really believe in 2035
我就说你假说真正相信2035年
If the sea level were to rise six meters
海平面要上升六公尺的话
you go home and see the one in your house
你回家去看看你家的那个
How far is it from sea level now
离海平面有多远现在
Average distance from sea level to Taipei
离海平面平均来说台北
Only four meters above sea level
离海平面是只有四公尺
The average means that half of the people are within four meters.
平均啊表示说一半的人是四公尺之内啊
Let alone six meters
那更不要说六公尺
How much is left in 2035
2035年还剩多少
How much is ten or twenty left?
还剩十二十多少
twenty four years
二十四年
Suppose my twenty-four years later
假说我的二十四年以后
if my house will be under the sea
我的房子会在海水底下的话
Then I'll sell the house right now
那我现在马上就把房子卖掉
Otherwise, when you see it, everyone will sell you
要不然你看到时候大家都要卖你
money is gone
钱都没有了
I can not afford it
我买不起
so so but that's fine too
所以所以不过这也很好
That is to say, so many of us
就是说我们那么多人
everyone went to see
大家都去看了
People rarely think about selling their house.
大家很少去想到要賣房子的
So it means that our education level in Taiwan
所以表示說我們台灣的教育水準
It is indeed relatively high
的確是比較高的
have your own judgment
有自己的判斷力
this is very important
這一點很重要的
Actually, I'm not just a joke
其實我這個也不是只是笑話
i traveled a lot
我跑了很多地方
In fact, we are Taiwan
其實就是我們台灣
This level of education
這個教育水準的層次
Everyone's attempt is relatively high
大家的嘗試是比較高的
I tell you it is definitely taller than Americans
我跟你講絕對比美國人高
american until now
美國人到現在
You see, 40% of people believe
你看還有40%的人相信
that what
那個什麼
when our world began
我們這個世界開始的時候
almost 4000 years ago
是差不多4000年前
He still believes so
到現在他都相信是這樣
Let alone how he would believe
那更不要說他怎麼會相信
this greenhouse gas
這個溫室氣體
these things
這些東西
This sea level is rising
这个海平面上升啊
4 to 8 meters
4到8公尺
This is needed
这个是需要啊
At least like that whole pawn in Greenland
至少就说像格林兰的那个整个的兵
Soldiers on land melt
陆地的兵融化
That pawn melted
那个兵融化是
It is estimated that the total melting is 7 meters
估计是全部融化是7公尺
If it is said that the soldiers in Antarctica melted a part
那假如说是南极的兵再融化一部分
Then that will be 4 to 8 meters beyond this
那那会那会超过这个4到8公尺
OK
OK
But this
可是这种
Soldiers in Greenland and the Melting of Soldiers in Antarctica
格林兰的兵跟南极的兵的融化
current melting rate
目前融化的速度
Some say fast, some say slow
有人说快有人说慢
This is currently very uncertain
这个目前是很很不一定
Of course, this variable value is very large
当然这这不定值是很大
The indeterminate value is large
不定值是很大
Nor can it be exaggerated to say that it is unlimited
也不能够说把它无限制的这个夸大
ah
啊
There are many problems in this aspect of Zhenfu Erdu
真富二都市在这方面是有很多的问题的
As for the dean of his fifteenth hospital, he is aware of the importance of this issue
那至于他十五院院长都警觉到这个问题重要性
that i believe that is a very good
那个我相信那是一个非常好的
result
结果
21st Century Climate Change
21世纪气候变化
In addition, of course, the number of extremely high temperature days will increase.
另外当然这个极高温日数会增加
Decrease in the number of extremely low temperature days
极低温日数减少
drought will be worse
旱灾会更严重
it's a sure thing
这是很确定的事情
In addition it has
另外它有
This is of course taken from the IPCC
这个当然是从IPCC拿下来
That is to say
也就是说
the one from the intergovernment group
跨政府小组的那个
climate panel results
气候小组的结果
it was originally in 2007
它本在2007的
The next one is to talk about in 2014
下一个是2014年要讲
to bring up
要提出来
In 2007 it also said
2007的它还说
Typhoons and torrential rains are likely to increase
颱风暴雨都可能会增多
will be more serious
会更严重
Now basically it's been
现在基本上它已经
think this part
认为这一部分
typhoons will increase
颱风会增加
or worse
或者更严重
I don't think it's clear now
现在认为并不清楚了
But the rain will increase
不过暴雨还是会增多
wait for us
等一等我们
Of course the question
当然会把这个问题
discuss with you
跟大家讨论一下
The increase in temperature just mentioned
刚才讲的温度的增加
it is mainly
它主要是
To see how we reduce greenhouse gases
要看到底我們對溫室氣體的減量
how to decide
怎麼樣決定
will increase the minimum temperature by 1.8 degrees
將增溫最小的1.8度
is called B1
是叫做B1的情況下
it is very optimistic
它是非常樂觀的
that is
就是說
current carbon dioxide
目前二氧化碳
Current global average emissions
目前的全球的平均的排放量
is almost 4 metric tons
是差不多4公噸
basically means
基本上也就是說
we start now
我們現在開始
Keep at 4 metric tons per person
每人保持在4公噸
assuming that
假設這樣的話
we can keep in
我們可以保持在
The temperature increase will only reach 1.8 degrees
增溫只會到1.8度
in this case
在這種情況下
by 2100
到2100年
CO2 will only increase to 450 PPM
二氧化碳只會增加到450個PPM
It's almost 400 now
現在已經很接近400了
So this seems unlikely
所以這個看起來是不大可能
will definitely exceed
一定會超過的
more than one case
超過比較多的一個case
called A2 case
叫做A2 case
Name case
Name case
basically follow nature
基本上是听齐自然
Don't worry about it
大家不必管
continue to emit greenhouse gases
继续放温室气体
in that case
那个情况下
In 210 it loves carbon dioxide
在210年它这个爱养化碳
would increase to almost 840 PPM
会增加到差不多840个PPM
That is three times the pre-industrial revolution
也就是工业革命前的三倍
in this case
在这种情况下
Global warming is almost four degrees
全球升温是差不多四度
This is of course what I just mentioned
这个当然就是我刚才提到的
The situation of B1 and A2 mentioned to you
跟大家提到的B1跟A2的情况
Let's draw the picture just now
我们把刚才那个图画在
On the map of 1000 years ago
刚才1000年的图上
What we just saw was 1000 years
我们刚才看到的是1000年
then 100 years
然后100年
Now add another 100 years
现在再加100年
is here
是到这里
Everyone noticed this rise
大家就注意到这个上升
it feels pretty scary
感觉上起来是蛮可怕的
from this angle
从这个角度来看
This estimate of sea level rise
这个海平面上升的估计
also estimated
也有估计
The current one, of course, is what we just saw
目前的当然这个是我们刚才看到的
Using the results obtained in the last century
用上一个世纪凉到的结果
This is the predicted result
这个是预测的结果
This forecast is the IPCC's 2007 forecast
这个预测是IPCC的2007的预测
Later at the meeting in Copenhagen
后来在哥本哈根的会的时候
An impromptu estimate of sea level rise
临时又做了一个海平面上升的估计
There are some people who think that the sea level will rise faster
有一些对认为海平面会升的比较快的人
make an estimate
做出来的估计
even faster people
即使是比较快的人
did you notice
大家注意到没有
By the year 2000, they estimate, of course, there are uncertainties
到2000年他们估计当然有不定性
At most, it is slightly more than one meter to 2000 years
最多最多也就是稍微超过一公尺到2000年
His middle point is still less than a meter
他那个中间点还是小过一公尺
Still less than a meter
还是小过一公尺
that
那个
rather than
而绝对不是
Both are 6 meters
都是6公尺
6 meters as mentioned by IPCC
IPCC講的6公尺
is problematic
是有問題的
Of course centuries later
當然在幾個世紀以後
Will it be 6 meters
會不會到6公尺
i think about greenhouse gases
我想溫室氣體的情況
if you continue
繼續下去的話
centuries later
幾個世紀以後
Of course it is possible to increase to 6 meters
當然是可能增加到6公尺
but we also know
可是我們也都知道
in petroleum gas
在石油煤氣
I'm afraid before 2050
恐怕2050年之前
basically
就基本上
No LOT of Petroleum Gas
沒有大量的石油煤氣
ready to dig
可以挖了
the coal itself
那煤本身
Of course there are almost 100 more years
當然還有差不多100多年
can dig
可以挖
but by then
不過到那時候
carbon dioxide emissions
二氧化碳的排放量
It is very uncertain
它的不定性非常大
so this
所以這個
that is to say centuries later
就是说几个世纪以后
This layout is very stable
这个布定性非常大
That use value is very small
那个使用价值就很小
I just talked about global issues
刚才讲的是全球的问题
here back to us Taiwan
这里回到我们台湾
Our Taiwan has increased in the past almost 100 years
我们台湾的过去差不多100年增加
The temperature increase is applied on the
温度的增加是在上涂
that past 100 years
那个过去100年
That 100+ year global temperature increase is undercoated
那个100多年全球的温度增加是下涂
you can see
大家可以看出来
it looks like that
它那个样子很像
First a temperature increase
先来一个温度增加
then relatively flat
然后比较平
Then another temperature increase
然后再来一个温度增加
this looks like
这个很像
This also means that we Taiwan is part of the global warming
这也表示说我们台湾是全球增温的一部分
But our warming
不过我们这个增温
Let’s talk about it carefully to see how much it heats up
大家讲说仔细的去看它增温有多少
is global warming
是全球增温
Let's say the 20th century was almost twice the global warming
就说二十世纪是全球增温的差不多两倍
The reason is now quite clear to us
这个原因现在我们也蛮清楚的
Mainly due to the influence of urban heat conduction effect
主要是都市的热导效应的影响
Influence of Urban Thermal Conductivity Effect
都市热导效应的影响
also takes us from 1961 to the present
也使我们从1961年到现在
almost 50 years
有差不多50年的时间
our main warming
我们主要的增温
Taiwan mainly heats up at night
台湾主要增温在晚上
rarely heats up during the day
白天很少增温
it's very interesting
这是很有趣的现象
OK
OK
wait we can see
等等我们可以看一下
in addition
另外
is that our rainfall intensity is changing
就是我们的降雨强度在变化
this is my personal opinion
这个是我我个人认为
Let's assume we're really worried about things in Taiwan
我们假设真正要担心台湾的事情
It's a matter of rainfall intensity
就是这个降雨强度的问题
The intensity of the rainfall and the heat wave
这个降雨强度跟热浪这些问题
are all changes that can be called extreme weather
都是可以叫做极端天气的变化
we know extreme weather is random
我们是知道极端天气是随意
This global warming changes
这个全球暖化而变化
The most obvious one is of course a heat wave.
那最明显当然是热浪啊
The change of that heavy rain and light rain
那个那个大雨小雨的变化
Also extreme weather changes
也是极端天气的变化
What about this change?
那这种变化呢
From the point of view of this pattern
从这个模式的角度来看
is very very difficult to predict
是非常非常难做预测的
that almost all patterns
那几乎所有的模式
There will be problems in this area
在这方面都都都会有问题
so what
那所以呢
This IPCC
这个IPCC啊
The impact of this extreme weather
对这种极端天气的影响啊
Although there are
虽然有有有
have done this for sure
有做这个很肯定的认为是
It will become more and more powerful
会越来越厉害啊
But he is still quite conservative
可是他他还是相当的保守
wait a minute we can see
等一等我们可以看
why is it like this
为什么是这个样子
Ah Taiwan heat wave
啊台湾热浪
This is us
这个是我们啊啊
One made in 2009
2009年做的一个啊
That Causa is our Posta Xu Qianzhong
那个Causa是我们Posta许前中
Then there is Chen Zhengping, a professor at National Taiwan University.
那还有台大教授陈正平
That
那
here it is
这里是
Taiwan
台湾
But from 1961 to 2005
但1961年到2005年
45-year mean temperature change
45年平均温度的变化
it's daytime
上面是白天
bottom is night
底下是晚上
blue is to reduce the temperature
蓝的是减少温度
red is to increase the temperature
红的是增加温度
Everyone knows it at a glance
大家一看就知道
increase temperature at night
增加温度都是晚上
especially ayutthaya
尤其是大城
increased temperature during the day
白天增加温度
real decent increase
真正像样的增加
only this station
只有这个站
Only the station is 3.5 kilometers away from the budget
只有站是预算3.5公里处
Of course he does not represent Taiwan
他当然他不代表台湾
he actually represents
他其实是代表
Represents the change in temperature over a large area
代表比较是大区域的温度的变化
So if you take Yushan away
所以你把玉山把它拿掉的话
Average daytime temperature in Taiwan
台湾的平均白天的温度
actually cooling down
其实是降温的
What is the real reason for the cooling
降温的真正的原因是什么
We also have quite a large thinning now
我们现在也有相当的大的薄落
It's the polluted gas that we exhale
是我们排出来的污染的气体
polluted gas
污染的气体
reflect sunlight back during the day
白天把阳光反射回去
so we environmental rats
所以我们环保鼠
working harder now
现在越来越努力
They really worked hard
他们的确也蛮努力了
Taiwan's pollution is getting less and less
台灣的污染越來越少
look carefully
你仔細看
especially taipei
尤其是台北
In the past 15 or 20 years in Taipei
台北過去差不多15年20年
Especially the reduction of this preemptive pollution
尤其是這種先服為力的污染的減少
more than doubled
減少不止一倍
so this is pretty good
所以這個是相當好的
But it also means
不過這也表示說
In the future we will be more and more
以後我們越來
The EPA is getting harder
環保署越來越努力
What we pay will go back to the card
我們付的都會回到證的去
OK
OK
At night because the sun has no effect
晚上因為陽光沒有影響
night temperature global warming
晚上溫度全球加溫
heated
有加溫
Then there is the thermal conduction effect also heating up
然後又有熱導效應也在加溫
So it gets hotter at night
所以晚上增溫特別厲害
look at taipei
台北你看
Between 45 years
45年之間
45 years of global increase
全球增加45年
A staggering 0.5 degrees increase
增加了不起0.5度
Here it increases almost 2 degrees
這裡增加差不多2度
2 degrees increase at night
晚上增加2度
The result in Taipei was quite a bad result
台北那结果是相当不好的结果
As you can see, Taiwan is Taiwan without Taipei.
大家看到没有台北就是台湾
This is a different place in Taiwan as a whole
这是台湾整个台湾不同的地方
Different colors represent different places
不同的颜色代表不同地方
Minimum temperature over 25 at night
晚上最低温超过25的
number of days in a year
一年的天数
OK
OK
Blue represents Taipei
蓝色是代表台北
did you notice
大家注意到没有
look
你看
It's over 25 degrees tonight
这个晚上超过25度
Said it was over 25 degrees outside
表示说外面超过25度
It must be definitely over 26 degrees in there
那里面一定是绝对超过26度
The government even allows you to turn on the air conditioner
政府都都都让你可以开冷气
So at that time, everyone must turn on the air-conditioning
所以那时候大家就一定开冷气
This air-conditioned night from before 1960
这个开冷气的晚上从前1960年
There are only more than 30 days when the air conditioner needs to be turned on at night
需要开冷气的晚上只有30多天
Now you see more than 100 days
现在你看多过100天
Taipei needs to turn on the air conditioner at night
台北需要开冷气的晚上
tripled
增加了三倍
This actually affects
这个其实影响是
very huge
非常大的
Just say no wonder our Aiyanghua carbon brand
就说怪不得我们的爱养化碳牌的
Everyone's brand is better than the whole world
每个人牌的都比全世界
How much more are we than the world average
我们比全世界平均增多多少
Does anyone know
有没有人知道
three times
三倍
someone knows this
这个有人知道
This is also one of the reasons
这个也是原因之一
look
你看
Taiwan in summer
台湾夏天的时候
The air conditioner is basically turned on everywhere at night
到处晚上基本上都是开冷气
that all
那所有
The other two big cities are not much better
另外两个大城也好不到哪去
Black
黑色的
the second most increased
增加的第二多的
The same goes for Tainan and Taichung
台南台中也是一样
Almost all Taiwan
几乎全台都有
The phenomenon of drinking more and drinking less
喝多喝少的这种现象
Although urban
虽然都市
I just said that it is urban heat conduction effect
我刚才讲是都市热导效应
But for us in Taiwan as a whole
可是我们台湾整个来说
because of the population density
因为人口密度的关系
We have all guides
我们有全导的那种
The tendency of the kind of thermal conduction effect
热导效应的那种的趋向
time relationship
时间的关系
I won't show you this picture
我就不给大家看这个图了
Tell me about the heat island effect
隨便講一下這個熱島效應
This is Chuo University Shake Center
這個是中央大學搖擦中心
Provided by Professor Liu
劉教授提供的
This is Taichung area
這個是台中地區
you see build plants
你看建植物去
Paddy field next to Dadu West
大渡西旁邊的水田
You see purple against this dark green
你看紫色對這個暗綠色
dark green here purple
暗綠色在這裡紫色
about six degrees
差差不多六度
This is a very cold effect
這個是非常大冷影響
daytime
白天
daytime heat wave
白天熱浪
OK
OK
At one point we said that the EPA said it was going to put a heat wave rack
我們有一度說環保署說要放熱浪架
or when the heat wave comes
或者是熱浪來的時候
outdoor sports
戶外活動的體育
Manual workers get a raise
體力勞動的要加薪
I will show him this about our Taiwan
這個我就給他看我們台灣
Days when the temperature exceeds 36 degrees
高溫超過36度的日子
Also different colors and different places
也是不同顏色不同地方
The real high temperature exceeds 36 degrees
真正高溫超過36度
looks a bit increased
看起來有點增加的
The obvious increase is my blue desk
明顯增加的就是我這個藍的台
Taipei is Taipei
台北 就是台北
Then, just look at the words of Taipei
然后呢 只视台北的话
Of course it's not about global warming.
那当然不是全球暖化的关系
It is all related to the thermal conductivity effect
是都是热导效应的关系
and the increase is not so large
并且增加的情形也不是那么大
Because this is 36 degrees
因为这个到底是36度
If you say it is 38 degrees
你假如说是38度
I believe this is not just a one or two day relationship
我相信这个并不是只视一两天的关系
So heat waves are basically not too serious a problem
所以热浪基本上不是一个太严重的问题
in Taiwan
在台湾
And the really serious problem is that we
而真正严重的问题是我们
The results of a study done in 2009
2009做的一个研究的结果
as far back as almost 10 years ago
远在差不多10年前
we noticed this
我们就注意到这个问题
in Taiwan
在台湾
all of taiwan
台湾的全部
Here is an article from our 2002
这里画的是我们2002年的一个文章
He just said that his information will be pushed back
把他就说把他的资料再往后推
This is all the rainfall in Taiwan
这个是台湾全部的降雨
Average rainfall throughout the year
全年的降雨平均值
This line is an average of 2 3 1 5mm
这条线是平均值2 3 1 5毫米
up and down
有上有下
But there is no long-term change
可是没有一个长期的变化
The second graph is the number of hours we have rain
第二个图是我们降雨的时数
it goes up and down
它随着上下
But it has a long-term change
可是它有一个长期的变化
Total rainfall is derived from rainfall hours
总降雨量出于降雨时数
that's the intensity of the rain
那是降雨的强度
did you notice
大家就注意到没有
When the rainfall intensity reached almost 80 years
就降雨强度到了差不多80年时候
all of a sudden increase
一下子就增差
increase
增加起来
just increased
就增加的
to a similar extent
程度有差不多
The average is almost 3 2.9
平均是差不多3 2.9
Then this has increased by almost 1
那这有增加有差不多1
That is an increase of 30%
也就是说增加了30%
rainfall intensity
降雨强度
increased by 30%
增加了30%
That's another point of view
那这是用另外一个角度来看
I just explained this to you
这个我刚才已经跟大家解释
say every 10 years on average
就说每10年平均
heavy rain here
这边强降雨
It's raining here
这边是中小雨
it has this tendency
它是有这种趋向
Increase in heavy rainfall
强降雨增加
Moderate rain decreases
中小雨减少
The whole world has seen this
全世界都有看到这个情形
We analyze the data of the United States
我们把美国的data分析
Also heavy rainfall is increasing
也是强降雨在增加
Moderate rain hasn't changed much
中小雨没有怎么变
This America is a comparison
这个美国是比较一个
interesting example
有趣的例子
is total rainfall in the United States is increasing
是美国的总降雨量在增加
This is different from Taiwan
这个跟我们台湾不一样
Our total rainfall in Taiwan
我们台湾的总降雨量
very little change
变化非常少
But America North America
可是美洲 北美洲
Total rainfall is increasing
总降雨量在增加
The result of this is
这样的结果是
Its heavy rainfall increases even more
它强降雨增加更厉害
not just
不只是
I mean the whole world has seen it
就说全世界都有看到
Increase in heavy rainfall
强降雨增加
Moderate rain decreases
中小雨减少
this in theory
这个在理论方面
now more and more mature
现在也越来越成熟
Year 2003
2003年
spring bass
春贝斯他
they published an article
他们发表了一个文章
put the past almost ten years
把过去差不多十年
A comparative summary of theoretical articles in this area
在这方面理论的文章做一个比较总结
conclude
做一个总结
It is basically now that the theory is getting more and more mature
它基本上现在理论越来越成熟
It's just that its quantification is still not very certain
只是它量化到现在还不是很确定
it basically says
它基本上是这样说的
According to the most basic principles of physics
按照最基本的物理的原理
Just increase the temperature by one degree
温度只要增加一度
Because most of the earth's surface is water
因为地球到底大部分是表面是水
water vapor on the sea
海面上的水蒸气
temperature increased by one degree
还温增加一度
will increase by about seven Percent
就会增加大约七个Percent
said
表示说
You added 7% more water vapor
你增加了7%水蒸气多了
if nothing else remains the same
什么其他东西都不变的话
Each rainfall should increase by 7%
每一个降雨应当都会增加7%
But heavy rainfall will increase even more
可是强降雨会增加的更多
why
为什么呢
Because 7% entered heavy rainfall
因为7%进到强降雨
Because heavy rainfall is usually a very large convective system
因为强降雨通常是一个很大很大的对流的系统
The convection system sucks in from the bottom
对流系统都是从底下吸进来
lots of air down there
很多底下的空气
its watery air
它带水气的空气
So this water vapor has increased by 7%
所以这些水气增加了7%
Once it enters the convection
它一进到对流里面
when it goes up
它就往上升的时候
It was water vapor when it went up
往上升的时候它本来是水气
will become
就会变成
go up and get cold
往上升就变冷
Turns into liquid water when cooled
变冷的时候就变成液态水
From water vapor to liquid water
从水蒸汽到液态水
it gives off what's called latent heat
它会放出来所谓的潜热
Liquid water turns to ice
液态水再往上升会变成冰
continue to emit shallow heat
继续放出浅热
Emitting shallow heat is for the study of meteorology
放出浅热是在研究气象方面来说
They think that making the convection more intense
他们认为使对流更强烈
In other words, you originally only increased by 7%
也就是说你本来只增加7%
But your convection is stronger
可是你对流更强烈了
That is to say, heavy rainfall
也就表示说强降雨
The increase will be much more than 7%
增加会远远超过7%
For this I used schematic
针对这个我用来示意图
That is to say, water vapor enters
就是说水气进来
It emits a shallow heat after entering
进来以后它放出浅热
Then make the convective system more intense
然后使对流的系统更加强烈
This is our estimate
这个是我们估计的
right to estimate
估计的权
No, we were meant to do global
不,我们本来是做全球
This is what we did for Taiwan
这个是我们针对台湾做的
Estimated using data from Taiwan
用臺灣的資料做的估計
What is this estimate?
這個是估計什麼呢
That is, when the global temperature increases by one degree
就是說全球溫度增加一度的時候
How will Taiwan's rainfall intensity change?
臺灣的降雨強度會有什麼樣的變化
then i just said
那我剛才說了
Let's just divide Taiwan's annual rainfall into
我們就說把臺灣整年的降雨分成
According to its rainfall intensity, it is divided into ten equal parts
按照它那個降雨強度分為十等分
Then we calculate the result that
然後我們算出來的結果就是說
The strongest ten percent of heavy rainfall
最強的百分之十的強降雨
Just one degree increase in global temperature
全球溫度只要增加一度
It increased by almost 140%
它就增加差不多140多%
almost doubled and a half
增加將近一倍半
Just one degree increase in global temperature increases
全球溫度只要增加一度增加
only heavy rainfall
只有強降雨
Thousands of ten percent heavy rainfall doubles and a half
千百分之十的強降雨增加一倍半
The light rain is decreasing
那中小雨都在減少
are decreasing
都在減少
the impact of this
那這個的影響
of course that means
當然就是說
I think everyone can imagine
我想大家都可以想像的
that
那個
I was introducing this just now
刚才我在介绍这个
Just say the old one
就说从前的那个那个
It was mentioned in ancient civilizations
古文明的时候就提到了
This heavy rainfall increases
这强降雨增加
This will increase flooding
这个就是会增加水灾
ok
ok
Then the top 10% is supposed to increase so much
那这个前10%的假如说是增加这么多
then you can imagine
那你可以想象
We actually count the top 1%
我们其实也有算前1%
Top 1% increase over 220%
前1%增加超过220%
we know this
这个我们知道
We counted the top 1%
我们算过前1%
the more intense kind of rain
就是更更强烈的那种降雨
10% stronger than 1% ahead
强10%跟前1%
Almost all the heavy rainfall brought by the typhoon
几乎都是台风带来的那种强降雨
The top 1% more than tripled
那个前1%增加2倍多
so this
所以这个
global temperature increase
全球温度增加
Increased chance of landslides and floods
土石流跟水灾的几率增加
will be very large
就会非常大
more than double more than double
超过一倍超过一倍
the reduction of the light rain
那小雨的减少
For example, in this
好比说在这个
winter and spring
冬天跟春天
The rain in Taiwan is almost all light rain
台湾的雨几乎都是小雨
After you reduce the light rain
你把小雨减少了以后
There will be problems with spring plowing in the second spring
第二年春天的春耕就会有问题
If you take a closer look at Taiwan's spring situation
大家假如仔细去看台湾的春天的情形
Spring plowing to do a simple statistics
春耕去做一个简单的统计
It can be noticed that the plowing rate of spring plowing in recent years
都可以注意到近年来春耕的修耕率
Much higher than 50 years ago
比50年前高太多了
Here I will give you a rough estimate.
这里我就说粗略的给大家估计一下
1950 to 2005
1950年到2005年
global temperature increase
全球温度增加
almost very close to 0.7 degrees
差不多很接近0.7度了
0.7% of each degree of Taiwan 140%
0.7成上台湾的每一度140%
almost 100%
几乎就是100%
That is to say
也就是说
You said it was this heavy rain that gave you
你讲说是这种强降雨给你的
brought the words of the flood
带来的是洪水的话
basically the basis of this flood
基本上就是这种洪水的基础
double the odds
機率增加了一倍
OK
OK
The light rain has also decreased relatively.
那小雨也有相對的減少
Then follow this effect
那接著這個影響
certainly
當然
this is what we have seen
這個是我們已經看到的
what has happened
已經發生的事情
Taiwan has
台灣已經
that in addition
那另外
The IPCC
這個IPCC
It is estimated that by 2035
都估計是到2035
will increase by about 0.7 degrees
會再增加差不多0.7度
that is to say
那也就是說
what we just said
我們剛才講的
turn it over again
再會翻一翻
OK
OK
So to this 2035
所以到這個2035
Taiwan's flood control
我們台灣那個防洪
Anti-landslide
防土石流
anti-sweat measures
防汗的措施
should be
應當是
in the 1950's
在1950年的
or earlier
或者更早的那個時候
These engineering facilities
這些工程設施
should be tripled
應當要增加3倍
increase by 3 times
增加3倍
sounds like it says yes
聽起來好像說是
we're going to take this
我們就是去把這個
Project tripled
工程增加三倍
I did ask people
我倒是問過人家
People say Tamsui River
人家說淡水河
The entire Tamsui River Basin in Greater Taipei
這個整個大台北的淡水河流域
Increase this flood control project
把這個防洪工程增加
don't say three times
不要說三倍了
even if you double
你即使是增加兩倍
do it again
重新弄一次
He said do it again
他說重新弄一次
how much do you want
你算要多少錢
He said to use photos to count
他說要用照來算
that is
就是說
so this
所以這個
Questions like this
像這種問題啊
ah british
啊英國
Because special attention has been paid to this aspect of climate change
因為對這方面氣候變化方面特別注意
they often come to my office
他們常常來來我辦公室
to talk about this
去談談這方面的問題
He said ah he said this is in our UK
他說啊他說這個在我們英國
There is also this phenomenon
也有這種現象
I said we I told others
我說我們我跟人家說
This is what we need for flood control
這個我們防洪要
to find a way
要要趕快想辦法
make him
把他
This flood protection measure re-enlarges it
這個防洪措施重新重新把它加大
He said
他說
I'm in the UK
我在我們英國
we also say
我們也是說
What a lot of engineering needs to be added
什麼很多工程需要加
But the government never
可是政府從來不做
he said why not
他說為什麼不做
He said it makes sense
他說也是有道理的
Think about it
你想想
he does this project
他做這個工程
wait till it's done
等到做完的話
timing
計時
Don't talk about four-year term
不要說四年的一任
He served eight years
他八年那一任
He can't even see when it's done
他都看不到那個做完的時候
He said there wasn't even a single vote
他說選票根本一票都沒有
He said why to do it
他說為什麼要去做
so they don't do it
所以他們都不去做
so he suggested we
所以他建議我們
later in Taiwan
以後要在台灣
set up a
成立一個
a complete
一個完全
independent
independent
completely independent
完全獨立的
How to say
怎麼說
to global warming
來全球暖化的
Oversight Team
監督小組
like
好像
Great Britain was formed
英國成立了
i miss us taiwan
我想我們台灣
will not be established
不會成立
basic solution
基本解決之道
that
那個
of course we know
我們當然知道
The basic solution is to prevent
基本解決就是阻止
the mitigation
這個mitigation
Of course, stopping global warming can reduce carbon
當然就是阻止地球暖化 皆能減碳
easier said than done
講起來容易做起來難
show everyone
給大家看一看
current carbon dioxide emissions
目前二氧化碳排放量
Still keep going up, all over the world
還是一直往上跑 全世界的
Taiwan is not left behind
我們臺灣也不落人後
I think I showed you this last time
這個我想我上次給大家看過
After 1980 to 2005
1980年以後 到2005
The grayest is our Taiwan
最灰的是我們臺灣
Take a break from the American people to increase
從美人士公頓一下增加
More than 12 metric tons increased by 3 times
超過12公頓 增加了3倍
The three worst countries in the world
世界最差的三個國家
we are now second only to them
我們現在僅次於他們
USA Australia and Canada
美國 澳洲 跟加拿大
Of course there are some very small countries in the middle
當然中間還有一些非常小的小國
here is only count
這裡是只算有
A country with a population of more than 10 million
有1000萬以上人口的國家
we are number four
我們是排名第四
All Western European countries and Japan are under us
所有的西欧国家日本都在我们底下
not to mention france
法国更不用说
France is this one
法国是这一条
OK
OK
china is here
中国在这里
China is now more than five
中国现在已经超过五了
It's over five now
现在已经超过五了
What are the main differences between France and Taiwan?
法国跟台湾主要不同在哪里
Does anyone know
有没有人知道
nuclear power
核电
Nuclear Power Now Sounds Dirty World
核电现在听起来是Dirty World
but
不过
This is mainly
这个主要是
France is different from us
法国跟我们不同的地方
Of course we're going to take us from 12 metric tons
当然我们要把我们从12公吨
reduced to 4 metric tons
减到4公吨
Because the target is 4 metric tons
因为目标是4公吨
we are now
我们现在是
Actually we may be over 12 metric tons
其实我们可能超过12公吨
to reduce to 4 metric tons
要减到4公吨
our estimate
我们的估计
Saving and improving efficiency may be almost 65% from 12-4
节约提高效率可能从12-4要差不多65%
20% of them may be saved and improved efficiency can be achieved
其中的20%可能接过节约跟提高效率可以做到
Here I specifically mentioned putting in a vegetarian
这里我特别提了放进一个素食
Vegetarianism is actually a very effective way
素食其实是一个很有效的办法
But it's easier said than done
可是讲起来容易做起来不容易
I'm basically a vegetarian for two days a week
我基本上每个礼拜恐怕是两天是素食
I'm not bad at other times
其他的时候我还不是不行
Vegetarianism is not only that it can save a lot of greenhouse gases
素食不只是它是可以节省不少的温室气体
It's on top of the greenhouse gases we're putting in right now
它最重要的是我们现在放进去的温室气体
it is slow to come out
它要出来是很慢的
It will basically take 100 years to come out
它要出来基本上要100年才会出来
100 years after we put it in now, it will still be heated for at least 50 years
我们现在放进去的100年以后都还在加热至少50年
Still at home a hundred years later
一百年以后都还在家
Most of it will come out in a hundred years
一百年以后它大部分会出来
But if you say vegetarian
可是你假如说素食的话
very powerful
就很powerful
vegetarian words
素食的话
If you say that many people are vegetarian
你假如说很多人素食
That's a lot of them now dedicated to raising cattle and sheep.
那就很多的现在专门用来养牛养羊的
Like Brazil he burned many souls
像巴西他烧了很多生灵
It's all about raising cattle and sheep
那都是去养牛养羊
then sell
然后卖出去
European places such as the United States and the United Kingdom
美国英国这种欧洲地方
A lot of farmland it can return to life
很多的农田它可以回到生灵
Because vegetarians need very little food
因为素食需要的粮食非常少
a lot less
少很多
If there is not so much food
那粮食不那么多的话
A lot of land can be released
很多的土地都可以放出来
back to life
就说回到生灵
It sucks carbon dioxide directly from the air
它是直接从空气中吸二氧化碳进来
down
下来
food very fast
粮食非常快的
several years
几年
can be done in a few years
几年就可以做到
If you don't believe me, it's true that none of us are vegetarians.
你不信讲说是我们真的没人素食
and say vegetarian
并且说素食
In fact, I am also quite excited
其实我也是蛮exciting的
Because every time I say vegetarian
因为每次说素食
People always say oops best man ever
大家总是说 哎呀 最好的男人
I also think it's hard to eat meat, but it tastes better
我也认为很难吃肉 还是比较好吃
But what?
可是呢
But do you know that when I was in college
可是你知不知道我读大学的时候
i have already said
我已经讲过了
everyone is younger than me
大家比我年轻
I didn't expect to go to college
没有想到我读大学
I am Taichung No.1 Middle School
我是台中一中
Treasure to send big
宝送成大的
OK
OK
Chengda has only three restaurants
成大只有三个餐厅
There are only three restaurants for boys
男生只有三个餐厅
a girl restaurant
一个女生餐厅
our boys restaurant
我们男生的餐厅
Everyone loves that third restaurant
大家都喜欢那个第三餐厅
It is better than modern
比较modern 比较好
Things to eat
吃的东西
we run every time
我们每次都跑
run to everyone
大家跑前去
we were
我们那时候
I'm basically never full
我基本上从来没吃饱过
I'm never full for breakfast
我早餐从来没吃饱过
That
那
at that time
那时候
I was in Chengda for four years
我在成大四年
that
那个
that rice bag
那个包饭
The price of the package meal has never changed
那个包饭价格从来没改变
That
那
guess how much a month
猜猜看一个月多少钱
how much?
多少啊?
any left?
还有没有?
Some people say 90
还有人讲90的
Wow
哇
If 90
假如90的话
I tell you
我告诉你
I'm not here today
今天我都不在这里
Then
然后
that
那个
I was
我那时候
this is really
这个真的是
It's the wind that blows
是这个风一吹来
i feel a little bit
我都会感觉有点
thin feeling
轻薄的感觉
at that time i
那时候我
Often less than 60 kg
常常都不到60公斤
I now
我现在
75 kg
75公斤
How much difference do you see
你看差多少
I'm not so fat now
现在我也不是那么胖
It was good at that time
那时候好受
we had breakfast
我们那时候早餐
90 is really
90真的是
a month
一个月
Think about it 180 a month
你想想180个一个月
one day
一天
How many
多少
6 pieces
6块
A meal is only 2 yuan
一餐只有2块钱
At that time, breakfast was less than two yuan
那时候早餐的话分不到两块钱
I guess for breakfast I'm afraid he put a dollar in it
我估计早餐恐怕他放了一块钱进去
The porridge we ate for breakfast
那个早餐我们吃的那个稀饭
pick that up
那个捞起来
You can't eat two bowls
你吃两碗你也吃不下了
ok then you say run faster
ok 那你说跑快一点
In the morning, I ran to fish the bottom
早上跑去捞底下的
This water will know me too
这个水都会 我也会
but that cook is smarter than you
不过那个厨师比你更聪明
they are not less
他们一点都不少
He cooked the porridge
他把那个稀饭煮的
Let’s just say the rice grains and the water
就说那个饭粒跟那个水的
no matter what height you put
无论你放在什么高度
it weighs the same
它那个重量是一样的
It's the same wherever you dig
你挖到哪里都一样
just like rivers and lakes
就跟江湖一样
So you eat, some people say why don’t you eat steamed buns
所以你吃 那有人说你怎么不吃馒头
I want to say when I hear this
我一听这话我都想说
I said oops there's a king in France
我说 哎呀 法国有一个国王
The lady said the sign up was hungry
那个太太说那个报名饥饿
no bread
没面包吃
He said how could these idiots not eat
他说这群傻瓜他们怎么不会去吃
do you want cake
吃蛋糕嗎
That no no no no steamed buns
那個沒有沒有沒有饅頭
it's like saying
這就好像說
It's not good for you to eat porridge
你吃稀飯多不好
Are you going to eat steamed buns?
去吃饅頭嗎
If there were steamed buns, I would not weigh 60 kg
假如有饅頭我也不會60公斤
I mean
我這個意思就是說
I used to eat very little meat
從前吃的肉很少
It's actually healthy
其實也是滿健康的
Just give us some steamed buns in the morning
只要早上給我們一些饅頭
That should actually be passable
那個其實是應當可以過得去的
That also means
那另外也是說
That means we eat meat in Taiwan now
就是說我們台灣現在吃肉
When do you think we eat meat
你想想我們什麼時候才吃肉
Actually very recently
其實很最近的事情
I'm afraid it will be 20 or 30 years.
恐怕也二三十年了不起
even americans
即使是美國人
The American who first started eating meat
美國人那個第一次開始吃肉
Guess when
大家猜猜看什麼時候
after World War II
二次大戰以後
They just started eating meat
他們才真正開始吃到肉
before World War II
二次大戰之前
they didn't eat the meat
他們並沒有吃到肉
the best proof is
那最好的證明是
1928 call for presidential campaign pioneer
1928年呼 for 總統的競選先員
He said you choose my words
他说你们选我的话
he said i promise
他说我保证
a chicken in every part
a chicken in every part
ah yes
啊就是
Chicken is the cheapest meat in America
Chicken是美国认为最便宜的肉
chicken
鸡肉
He said you just choose me
他说你只要选我
i promise you go home
我保证你们回家
Every night there is a chicken in that pot
每天晚上那个锅子里面有只鸡
he chose
他选上了
So what does this represent?
那不这个代表什么呢
Let's say in 1928 most people in the United States
就说1928年美国大部分人
no chicken for dinner
没有鸡可吃晚上
because if there is chicken to eat
因为假如有鸡可吃
why choose it
何必选它呢
so that
所以那个
Then I didn't have to eat for 28 years
那后来28年没得吃
as you can imagine
大家可以想象
later in the 1930s
后来到30年代
Needless to say
用不用说了
America in the 1930s
30年代美国那时候
the Great Panic
那个经济大恐慌
it's over
就完蛋了
then fight
然后打仗
Not to mention what kind of meat to eat when fighting a war
打仗更不要说吃什么肉了
so basically
所以基本上是
The United States probably didn't eat meat until the 1950s
美国恐怕50年代才吃到肉
Europe is nothing compared to the 60s
欧洲没比60年代
Nothing like the 70s, our 80s
没比70年代 我们80年代
Mainland China in the 1990s OK
中国大陆90年代 OK
so we eat meat is very recent
所以我们吃肉是很最近的事情
We were generally not meat-eating animals in the past
我们一般从前并不是吃肉的动物
Eating so much meat is actually bad for your health
那吃那么多肉其实也是对健康与不好
So here's a chance to spread the word
所以这里趁机宣传一下
Naf carbon energy
那非碳能源
Of course this is not possible
这个当然是不行的
I guess vegetarians can't do it
我估计素食大家也办不到
So always look for non-carbon energy
所以总要找非碳能源
Take a look at non-carbon energy
非碳能源大家看看
Solar energy is of course endless
太阳能当然是无穷无尽
but expensive
可是贵的要命
If we all use solar energy
假如我们都用太阳能
Basically everyone does nothing
基本上大家什么东西都不要做
just buy solar
就只买太阳能
So water power wind power sea
所以水力风力海的
This sounds good
这个都是说起来好听
Right now, let's actually do it
目前就说真正要做实际要做
we want to add
我们要加
Taiwan's water power is good
台湾的水力是不错的
But it's all used up now
可是目前都用掉了
but about 2% to 3%
但差不多2%到3%
that's pretty good too
那也是蛮不错的
Reproductive power can indeed be a lot
生殖能的确可以不少
But this reproductive energy is the same as food
可是这个生殖能就是跟食物一样的
it you use a lot of food to grow
它你用很多食物去生长
reproductive energy words
生殖能的话
This whole food is going to get really expensive
这个整个食物会变得非常贵
So it's not very feasible
所以都可行性都不高了
what's left
剩下的只剩何能
After the earthquake in Japan, no one dared to say how
然后日本这个一地震再也没人敢说何能
so i don't say anything
所以我也不说了
That is to say, there is no solution
也就是说无解
OK, this is actually unsolvable at the moment
OK 这个其实目前是无解
I don't even remember this
这个我都不记得
there's a geoengineering we're almost done with
有一个地球工程我们快结束了
You can come back after taking a nap
大家打瞌睡也可以回来了
That geoengineering is a pretty interesting thing
那个地球工程是一个蛮有趣的东西
Geoengineering has been talked about recently
地球工程最近有不少人在谈
In fact, we have been talking about it for twenty or thirty years.
其实谈了已经有二三十年了
the simplest and most feasible
最简单最可行的
The first one is afforestation
第一个就是说造林
But afforestation is impossible without trees
可是造林没有树实是不可能的
currently limited area
目前面积有限
But if you have a solid word
可是你有树实的话
Afforestation is a pretty good way
就造林是相当不错的一条路
Everything else has it's very serious problems
另外一些东西都是都有它非常严重的问题
But now everyone knows
可是现在大家都知道
we do air pollution
我们做空气污染的
do the environment do the climate
做环境的 做气候的
We all know that the stratosphere adds some pollutants
我们都知道平流层加一些污染物
add some lurking power
加一些潜伏为力
like a volcano
像火山为力
It is currently very feasible
目前看在非常可行
what's the only bad thing about it
它唯一的不好处是在什么呢
It is tantamount to putting a pollutant
它等于说放一个污染物
Into a stratosphere to fight
进到一个平流层去来对抗
another artificial this this
另外一个人为的这个这个
carbon dioxide
就是污染的爱养化碳
Well
呃
That is to say, from this direction
就是说从从这个方向来想
he is he is a comparison to everyone
他是他是一个比较大家
something you don't want to accept
不大愿意接受的东西
but i'm guessing
不过我在猜
ah
啊
If say another ten or twenty years, the real problem
假如说再过十年二十年真正问题
big
大了
like this
像这种
Well
呃
that that that
那个那个
The problem of extreme weather becomes very big if
极端天气的问题变得非常大的话
Well
呃
there will be a united nations may
会有联合国可能会
authorized
授权
do some experiments on this
做一些这方面的实验
Because of this experiment
因为这个实验啊
nature has
自然界已经
Experiments that have been given to us
已经给我们的实验
and the experiment is valid
并且这个实验是有效
and his
并且他的
It has very little side effects
他的副作用非常小
what is that
那个是什么呢
It's a volcano
就是火山
most everyone remembers
最大家最记得
Should be the one from the Philippines
应当是菲律宾那个
year 1991
1991年
Volcanoes in Pingan Tubu
平安图布的火山
After that eruption, there are many things
那个爆发以后有很多东西
its explosive
它那个爆发的物
Enter the safe layer
进到平安图层
In 1992, 1993
在1992、1993年
global temperature
全球的温度
It has dropped by about 0.2 to 0.3 degrees
降了有差不多0.2到0.3度
two full years
整整两年
0.2 0.3 degrees down
降了0.2 0.3度
you see a small volcano
你看一个小火山
Drop 0.2 0.3 degrees
降0.2 0.3度
The world has only increased by 0.6 degrees in 100 years
全球100年才增加0.6度
so you just do
所以你只要做
make three small volcanoes
做到三个小火山
the whole 100 years
就可以把整个100年
can get it back
可以弄回来
So it seems to work
所以看起来是可行
just say now
目前就说
you use a big plane
你用大飞机
or a big rocket
或者是大火箭
send this
送这种
even with big balloons
甚至用大气球
Sending Pollutants to Stratosphere
送污染物到平流省
not very difficult
并不是很困难的事情
this is promising
这个是有希望的
So don't think it's hopeless
所以大家不要认为是没希望
But
可是
even if there is hope
即使是有希望
I guess until the United Nations
我估计等到联合国
when approved
批准的时候
I'm afraid it will be decades later
恐怕也是几十年以后
within these decades
在这几十年以内
We in Taiwan should do debugging
我们台湾自己应当是做调试的动作
That is to say, for such extreme weather
也就是说针对这种极端天气
this flood drought
这种洪水 旱灾
our government
我们政府
The real thing to say is that you should swim up and down
这个真正的说起来其实是应当游上而下
our government in this regard
我们政府在这方面
Measures against floods and droughts
在防洪防旱措施
really need to work hard
实在是有需要去努力
I think this is quite important
我想这个是相当重要
At this time, I also want to talk a little bit
在这时候我也要稍微讲一下
Our Research on Extreme Weather
我们对极端天气的研究
currently in this
目前在这方面
There are still many places that do not fully agree
还有很多地方并不是完全认同的
Some people think that the result of what we do
有的人认为我们做的结果
maybe a little too big
可能是太大了一点
Because IBCC says
因为IBCC讲的
The result obtained is relatively small
得到的结果是比较小的
Small quite a lot
小蠻多的
10 times smaller
有小10倍
So IBCC itself is now Evaluating this problem
所以IBCC現在本身也在Evaluate這個問題
they are not quite
他們也不完全
did not fully accept our view
並沒有完全接受我們的這種看法
That is, the global temperature increases by one degree
就是說全球溫度增加一度
This strong drop will also increase a lot
這個強降也會增加很多
Especially where the tail is low
尤其是低尾度的地方
But I think this information
可是我想這個這方面的資料
more and more complete
越來越完備
The model will get better and better in the future
模式以後會越來越好
We should have a more affirmative answer to this question from time to time.
這方面問題我們應當時會有比較肯定的答覆
took everyone's time
多花了大家一些時間
so thank you all
所以謝謝大家
ok
ok
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you Director Liu
謝謝劉主任
We still have ten minutes
我們現在還有十幾分鐘
I don't know if there is any problem doing it
不知道在做有沒有什麼問題
to bring up for discussion
要提出來討論
A rare opportunity
機會難得
please
請
Small quite a lot
小蠻多的
thank you all
謝謝大家
Thanks
謝謝
Sorry teacher
老師不好意思喔
you just mentioned
你剛才有提到說
This is in the part that lowers greenhouse gases
這是在那個降低溫室氣體的部分
parts of some so-called earth factories
的一些所謂地球工廠的部分
The first part mentions reforestation
那第一個部分提到是在造林
Well one thing we're curious about is
好那我們好奇的一件事情是
why must feel
為什麼一定要感覺
What you just said is that
您剛才的說法是說
There is an absolute relationship between tens and afforestation
數十跟造林之間有絕對的關係
But the part like Taiwan
可是像台灣的部分
There is a lot of farmland in the south-central
中南部有很多的農地
Well, it's all presented now
好不是現在都呈現
no situation
沒有縱使的狀況
Then why is the afforestation part not considered in
那為什麼造林的部分不考慮是在
part of flat land
平地的部分進行
For example, choose some fast-growing bridge trees
例如說選一些生長快速的橋木
Then it is the substance itself to carry out photosynthesis
那它本質物本身進行光合作用
It can consume a lot with the fixed open space
它就可以大量的消耗跟固定空地中的
carbon dioxide
二氧化碳
If only some of the high ornamental value
如果只要一些具有高度觀賞價值
And it is a fast-growing large bridge tree
而且又是生長快速的大型的橋木
it is not itself a
它本身不是就是一個
Is it a good solution?
很好解決的一個方案嗎
Thanks
謝謝
what you said is absolutely correct
那個你講的完全完全正確
not the only one you say
不唯一的你就說
something you didn't notice
你沒有注意到的一點
That is to say, you put these things in Taiwan
就是說你把台灣的這些
It's all flat bottom to reforestation
就是全部的平底去造林
that's also very very small
那也是非常非常小的
Taiwan is a small place after all
台灣到底是個小地方
So our afforestation
所以我們這個造林
The problem is the area
問題就是面積了
The problem is area
問題就是面積
this is
這個是
because you think about it
因為你去想想看
A place like America
那個像美國那種地方
You see how much it used to be covered by forest
你去看它從前的森林覆蓋有多少
How much forest cover is there now
現在的森林覆蓋有多少
that is far
那個差很遠
unless somewhere like that
除非像那種地方
that big place
那個大地方
Big places like America and China
美國 中國那種大地方
afforestation on a large scale
去大面積的造林
You want such a large area of ​​afforestation
你要那樣的大面積造林
food production must be
就必須把糧食的生產
pull it to the vegan stage
把它拉到素食的那種階段
there is hope
那才有希望
Otherwise, your area will never be enough
要不然你那個面積永遠不夠
Taiwan you got it all
台灣你全部弄贏的
make a little
弄一點點
ask Mr. Liu
请问一下刘老师
You use Taiwan's data to see the intensity of rainfall
您用台湾的资料来看降雨的强度
The relationship between temperature change and rainfall
气温变化跟降雨上的关系
Do you also do global
您也做全球的吗
Global results are similar
全球的结果是类似的
Yes
是的
our global results
我们全球的结果
I remember the global result being slightly smaller than this
我记得全球的结果比这个稍微小一点
No more than about 110 to 120
没比到差不多110到120左右
In fact, it is like saying that we do lower-dimensional
其实好比说我们做更低维度的
better than Taiwan
比台湾还厉害
Excuse me, what did you just say about geoengineering?
请问一下你刚讲到地球工程中
Stratosphere plus some micro-arc melody thing
平流层加上一些微弧旋律的事
Ask him if there is any risk
请问一下他有没有风险存在
Since you said he is currently more viable
既然你说他是目前比较可行
Why does the United Nations have to take some time to do something like this
为什么联国还必须要透过一些时辰来做这样的事
Many people have thought about the side effects
对 副作用很多人都想过了
i mean emphatically
我就是说强调
nature is already doing
自然界已經在做了
you don't care if we do or not
你不管我們做不做
The best ever
那個從前做的最厲害的
Actually is an interesting question
Actually是一個蠻有趣的問題
that is to say around
就是說在差不多
about 700,000 years ago
對差不多70萬年前
That so-called one called
那個號稱有一個叫做
Poba TOBA
Poba TOBA
Poba this Indonesian one
Poba這個印尼的一個
A volcanic eruption in Indonesia
印尼的一個火山爆發
What is that volcanic eruption claimed to be?
那個火山爆發號稱是是什麼
It's what we've heard about volcanic eruptions anyway.
反正是我們所聽過火山爆發的
A hundred times that big volcano
上百倍的那個大火山
that big volcano erupted
那個大火山爆發
It is said that an earth
聽說是造成了一個地球上
That creature would be that extinct one
那個生物會那個絕滅的一個
very big one
非常大的一個
I speak
我講
No
No
70 super
70超
to 700,000 years
對 70萬年
700,000 years ago
70萬年前
to 700,000 years ago
對 70萬年前
70 less
70少
Yes do 70ë‚˜
對做70나
like that big volcano
像那種大火山
after it explodes
它爆了以後
It's been cold for a long time
也就是冷了很久
Basically food production will have problems
基本上食物的生產都會有問題
there are also people
也有人
the Big Bang 700,000 years ago
把70萬年前的大爆炸
that did happen
那的確發生了
that big bang is thought to be
那個大爆炸被認為是
Humanity
人類
Just now from that Russi
剛才講從那個Russi
3 million years to now
到現在300萬年
say human
說人類
There was barely a volcanic eruption 700,000 years ago
幾乎沒有過70萬年前的火山爆發
Vipassana
內觀
what we never said
我們講沒過的話
you and i are not here
你我都不在這
It is said that there is a theory that talks about people.
号称是有的theory说人的那个那个那个
that is paired
就是说配对的
Because of your pairing, you can give birth
因为你的配对才能够生人
The effective pairing minimum for pairing is reduced to almost
配对的有效的配对最低降到差不多
The worst is the worst estimate
最就是说最坏的估计是说
There are only a thousand pairs left
只剩一千对的人在那里
so our genes
所以我们的基因
Claiming to be our genes until now
号称是我们的基因到现在
The one with only a thousand pairs
那个只有一千对的人
Actually very outspoken
其实很无讳
people are a bit outspoken
人家有点无讳
our gene
我们这个基因
Not too wide
各不过宽
that
那个啊
so the volcano erupted
所以火山爆发
the effects it causes
它引起的这些影响
ah
啊
as far as I can tell
目前来说
This small, medium-sized volcano
这个小小中型的火山
we are pretty sure
我们有相当大的把握
then we
那我们
We use this artificial method
我们用用这种人为的方法
put this pollutant in
放这种污染物进去
we can
我们又可以
put where we want
我们要的地方放
and again we want
并且再要我们要
put it at the time you want to do it
要做的那个时间点放
and to the stratosphere
并且到平流层呢
as soon as we stop
我们一停下来
stratosphere back to troposphere
平流层回到对流层
We've all figured this out
这个我们都有算过
is only two years
是只要两年的时间
That is to say, if you do something wrong
也就是说万一做错了
just two years
就是两年
like the one in the philippines
像菲律宾的那个
after entering
进去了以后
two-year effect
两年的效应
Very small by the third year
到第三年就很小了
not in the future
以后就没有
so this
所以这个
i'm guessing
我在猜
By the time
到时候
everyone is
人都是
lazy
比较懒惰的
That is to say, take the simplest method
就是说取一个最简单的方法
to solve
去解决
Teacher, what you just said
老师你刚刚讲的那个
a hundred years
一百年
drop in temperature
气温降低
raise zero point six degrees
升高零点六度
Then ask this 0.6 degrees
那请问这个零点六度
Let's say we start from
比如说我们从
alpine
高山
When descending from high altitude to low altitude
从高海拔往低海拔降的时候
that temperature will naturally decrease
那个温度会自然降低
For example, from the Central Plains Institute
比如说我们从中原院
Going out to the city hall 101 may increase the temperature by several degrees
出去到市政府101可能溫度就增加了好幾度
So how is this 0.6 degree calculated?
那這個0.6度是怎麼算出來的
That is to say, the 0.6 degree you mentioned is one
就是說你講的0.6度是一個
what kind of thing
一個什麼樣的東西
The second is to say
第二就是說
The temperature decreases by one degree for every 100 meters increase in altitude
海拔每升高100公尺氣溫就降低一度
So are we this Global warming?
那我們是不是這個Global warming
Why use degrees to express
為什麼要用度來表示
what does this mean
這個度代表著什麼意義
that is
就是說
Will humans evolve as the temperature rises?
當溫度升高的時候人會不會跟著進化
Maybe we can live with 40 degrees by then
可能到時候我們可以忍受40度
If you can't stand it, you'll hang up
不能忍受你就全部掛掉
So I have been thinking about this plus or minus two degrees C
所以我一直在想說這個什麼正負二度C
Could it be an ad for a politician
會不會是一個政客的廣告
If for an ecologist
如果對一個生態學家來講
it represents a
它代表著一個
What is the degree of coming and going?
到底度來度去是度什麼東西
i want to ask
我想問一下
answer your questions
回答您的問題
this degree
這個度
that is
就是說
the two of us
我們兩個
There has to be a measure for these things
这些东西总得有一个度量衡
Do you think why Qin Shihuang wanted to unify these things?
你想当初秦始皇为什么要统一这些东西
he has
他是有的
He is hoping to get something
他是希望弄一个东西
something we can all accept
我们大家可以接受的一个东西
to do this unit
来做这个单位
So why do you say degrees
所以您讲的度为什么要度
This means that everyone is like European and American countries
这就说大家像欧美国家
In fact, they have always been reluctant to use this degree
其实一直他们不愿意用这种度
He used that Fahrenheit
他都用那个Fahrenheit
He said to use that degree of Fahrenheit
他就说用那个华氏度
So he doesn't use our speed
所以他那个就不是用我们的度
So it's just all together
所以度只是大家合在一起
A unit that can communicate with each other
能够互相沟通的一个单位而已
not nothing great
并不是没有什么了不起的
How much does the global temperature increase
那至于全球温度增加多少度
that it is cool in different parts of the world
那个它是全球不同的地方凉
After it cools down, go to the average
凉到了以后去平均的
not like what you said
不像您所讲的
It's colder here
随随便便到了这里是比较冷
It is actually fixed
它其實是在定點
Do it all over the world
在全球都有做
Tens of thousands of observations
上萬點的觀測
So 0.5 degrees is a big number
所以0.5度是一個很大的數字
that number global temperature
那個數字 全球的溫度
It's not easy for you to get 0.5 degrees like this
你要這樣0.5度是很不容易的事情
There was a French scholar named De Rijin
是有一位法國的學者叫德日晉
i forgot his french way
我忘了他法國的那樣
He is a hundred years old
他是本世紀上百年
Also stayed in China for a while De Rijin
也在中國待過一段時間 德日晉
I remember he came up with a theory
我記得他提出一個理論
He said the earth is slowly cooling
他說地球在慢慢寒冷化
Is this the exact opposite?
這個是不是跟剛好相反
Many people have mentioned this
這個很多人提過
Of course the most famous person
當然最有名的這個人
His name is Milankovic
他叫做Milankovic
He's a Sirvia man
他是一個Sirvia的人
Sirvia is now called the year before
Sirvia現在叫做從前那一年
a place in yugoslavia
南斯拉夫的一个地方
it was in 1943
它是在1943
1920 during the war I remember
1920大战的时候我记得
In 1943 a
1943年提出来一个
that is to say globally
就是说全球
Global temperature of ice and air versus flying ice and
全球温度的冰和气跟飞冰和
The theory of temperature change with ice and air
跟煎冰和气最温度的变化的理论
That is to say, the orbit of the sun and the earth
就是说太阳跟地球这个轨道的
some regular changes
一些有规律的变化
Make the earth ice and air once every 100,000 years
使地球每十万年来一次冰和气
After it put forward this theory
它提出来这个理论以后
It was raised in 1943 until it died
1943年它提出来一直到它死
It is the object of cancellation
它都是人家取消的对象
People say it's unlikely to be true
人家说不大可能是对的
it says so
它讲的那么
Speaking of theory, it is quite complicated.
理论说起这话也是蛮复杂的
Now of course it doesn't look that complicated
现在当然看起来好像不是那么复杂
But his theory lasted until 1978-80
不过他那个理论一直到1978到80那阵子
Get out the data of the sunken objects on the seabed
海底的沉电物data弄出来
Let's find out all the previous temperatures
我们把从前的温度全部找出来
As a result, I found out the previous temperature and put it together with his temperature.
结果从前温度找出来跟他的温度放在一起
almost identical
几乎是一模一样的
So now everyone thinks he's great
所以大家现在都认为他很厉害
But he's been dead for a long time
不过他已经死了好久了
Your question was never answered
从来没有得到回答您的问题
That is to say, the glacier
就是说冰河起
it cools down very slowly
它降温很慢
It will take almost 10 years for the temperature to drop
降温都差不多要10年
but it heats up
可是它升温了
not 10 years
不是10年
That is to say, it takes 100,000 years for the temperature to cool down.
就是说降温要10万年升温
It only takes 10,000 years to heat up
只要一萬年就升溫
We are now in Jianbingheqi
我們現在在兼兵和旗
Between the two soldiers and the flag
這兩個兵和旗之間
some people think
有的人就認為
The time when we were soldiers and flags
我們兼兵和旗的時間
It's been almost 13,000 years
已經差不多1.3萬年
13000 years is quite a long time
13000年已經是蠻長了
Should go back to the next pawn and flag
應當要回到下一個兵和旗
some people think so
有人是這樣認為
But most people think
不過大部分的人都認為
Our next soldier and flag are still far away
我們下一個兵和旗還遠
still far
還比較遠
Looks like at least 10,000 years
好像至少還有1萬年
so
所以
i think there's every question
我想還有每一個問題
Teacher Liu, I would like to ask
劉老師我想請教一下
Mitigation and adaptation are two different concepts
減緩跟調適是兩個不同的概念
But between the two
不過這兩個之間
actually related
實際上是有關係的
Recently, I noticed some related news reports
最近我注意到一些相關資訊的報導
especially france
尤其是法國
Reduced cooling water capacity due to heat wave
因為熱浪造成冷卻水能力的降低
Then follow this operating specification
然後按照這個運轉的規範
it's running down load
它要降載運轉
In the end, the lack of electricity has to import electricity from the UK
到最後缺電要從英國進口電力
that means say
那表示說
when
當
good slowing tool
很好的一個減緩的工具
such as nuclear energy
比如說核能
Hypothetically, this natural disaster or climate change factor
假設考慮這種自然災害或是氣候變遷的因素
it might have a big discount on it
它可能對它會打了一個很大的折扣
reduce its ability to slow down
降低它減緩的能力
Then I think more about the incident in Japan's Hudao Island.
那以日本胡島這個事件我想更
Even
更
Everyone is more impressed
大家更有印象
Of course Hu Dao is not necessarily related to climate change
當然胡島不一定跟氣候變遷有關係
but at least it's a natural disaster
但是它至少是自然災害
That is to say, nuclear energy is a very good mitigation tool
就是說原來核能是很好的減緩的工具
But under natural disaster
可是在自然災害之下
it becomes a question mark
它變成是一個問號
Can it be used as a long-term view
是不是可以作為長久來看
Can it be used as a mitigation tool
是不是可以作為一個減緩的工具
This is the first one
這是第一個
First
第一個
first issue
第一個議題
from here
那從這邊
I want to derive the real thing I want to ask is
我要衍生真正的想請教的是
For Taiwan
就台灣地區
Because I saw some reports recently
因為最近我看到一些報導
That is to say, according to the assessment of the world risk company
就是說 根據世界風險公司的評估
Taiwan is actually a high-risk area
台灣事實上是屬於高風險的地區
He said that it seems to include the number of three disasters
他說 好像包括三種災害的數目
Seems like a 76 chance
好像是機率達到76
There is probably such an assessment
大概有這樣的一個評估
Let's assume that back to the first premise I mentioned just now
那假設回到剛剛我提的第一個前提
Suppose so what I want to ask is to say
假設所以我想請教的就是說
For Taiwan from the perspective of climate change or natural disasters
就台灣從氣候變遷的角度或自然災害的角度
Taiwan compared to the world average
台灣相較以世界的平均值
Is it really a high-risk area?
是不是真的是高風險的地區
If so
那假設是的話
In contrast to what Professor Liu mentioned just now
那在對照剛剛劉教授有提到
we are in mitigation
我們在減緩方面
From 4kg to 12
從4公斤增加到12
In fact, it is disadvantageous in this respect
事實上在這方面是不利的
Then suppose we add this
然後假設又加上這個
From the perspective of disaster
從災害這個角度
that's even worse
那更是雪上加霜
So what I really want to ask is to say
所以我真的想請教的是說
The region of Taiwan compared to the world average
台灣這個地區相較於世界的平均值
From the perspective of climate change or natural disasters
從氣候變遷或是自然災害的角度
Is it really as assessed by the risk company?
是不是真的如風險公司所評估的
is a high risk area
是高風險的地區
Thanks
謝謝
good question
這個問題很好
But your question
不過你這個問題
basically i think what you said
基本上我是認為你講的
that's true as far as i know
那據我所知都是正確的
It's actually quite easy to answer
其實也是滿容易回答
Think about how big our Taiwan is
你想想我們台灣那麼一點點大
Four typhoons come every year
每年來四個颱風
Almost all four typhoons will bring good rain
四個颱風幾乎都會帶來好雨
So the probability of a flood is
所以洪水的機率是
It is deadly high compared to many countries
比起很多國家來說都是高的要命
Especially for the entire Pacific Ocean
尤其是整個太平洋來說
This type of typhoon is stronger than the Atlantic typhoon
這種颱風比大西洋的颱風
average is strong
平均都是来得强烈
So we in Taiwan are rushing again
所以我们台湾又是正好冲
The typhoon is coming towards us
台风都是冲着我们来
Of course there is always someone worse than us
当然还有 总有比我们更差的地方
In terms of typhoon, you go to the Philippines
以台风来论 你去看看菲律宾
that's really what you do every year
那真的是你每年每年那个
Soak in water all day long
一天到晚泡水
we died hundreds of people
我们死上百人
we feel very unacceptable
我们感觉到非常无法接受
You go to see the people who die in typhoons every year in the Philippines
你去看菲律宾每年台风死的人
If he can reach less than a hundred people
假如他能到达百人以下的话
he's overjoyed
他已经乐得要命了
So the typhoon is actually very powerful
所以其实台风是很厉害
But the Philippines has fewer earthquakes than us
可是菲律宾的地震比我们少
So Taiwan has many earthquakes and typhoons
所以我们台湾地震多 台风多
what more
还有什么多啊
For our population, it is more worrying
对 我们这个人口是比较愁蜜
Then our Han disaster is stronger
然后我们这个汉灾比较强烈
Everyone thinks that 2500 mm of water is a lot of water for us a year
這一點大家都認為我們一年2500毫米的水是很多的
2500 mm lot of water
2500毫米水很多
But because of the large population
可是因為人口多
Average water resources per person
每個人平均得到的水資源
In fact, Taiwan ranks far behind in the world.
其實我們台灣在世界是排很後面
further back than mainland China as we know it
比我們所知道的中國大陸還後面
Mainland China seems to be shared by everyone
中國大陸好像是每個人分的
twice as much as us
還是我們的兩倍
So yes ours is a high risk zone
所以的確我們的是高風險區
plus this earthquake
那加上這種地震
Make this nuclear energy no way to use in Taiwan
使這個核能沒有辦法來利用在台灣
It makes our action of slowing down in Taiwan even more
更使我們這種在台灣做這個減緩的動作
looks very difficult
看起來是非常的困難
very difficult
非常的困難
well because the time is just right
好 因為時間剛剛好
we are very grateful for this today
我們今天非常感謝這個
Professor Liu Shaocheng is very strong
劉少成教授非常強烈的
I beg you ì˜ Athen Kaixing
我拜託您영 Athen 開興